<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A translation of the booke of nature, into the vse of grace Performed and principally intended for the benefit of those who plead ignorance, or they are not book-learned, or that they want teachers and so thinke to excuse themselues in their sinnes. By William Evans, Mr of Arts of St Mary Hall in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Evans, William, b. 1598 or 9.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13494</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837601</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177089</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240895458</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10597</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S101798</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99837601e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13494)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 788:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A translation of the booke of nature, into the vse of grace Performed and principally intended for the benefit of those who plead ignorance, or they are not book-learned, or that they want teachers and so thinke to excuse themselues in their sinnes. By William Evans, Mr of Arts of St Mary Hall in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Evans, William, b. 1598 or 9.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield printer to the Vniversity, and are to be sold by Thomas Huggins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:1"/>
            <p>A TRANSLATION of the Booke of NATVRE, into the Vse of GRACE. PERFORMED AND PRINCIPALLY intended for the benefit of those who plead ignorance, or that they are not <hi>Book-learned, or that they want teachers and so thinke to excuse themselues in their sinnes.</hi> By WILLIAM EVANS, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> of Arts of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Mary Hall in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor 3.1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>And I brethren, could not speake vnto you as vnto spirituall, but as vnto car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, even as vnto Babes in Christ. I haue fed you with milke and not with strong meat.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 6.19.</hi>
               </bibl> I speake after the manner of men, because of the infirmity of your flesh.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Lichfield</hi> Printer to the Vniversity, and are to be sold by <hi>Thomas Huggins.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:2"/>
            <p>time fishing with <hi>one bait,</hi> and sometime with <hi>another;</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time vsing one forme of speech, and sometime another; and all to <hi>prepare the way of the Lord, and to make his paths straight, and plaine</hi> for men to walke in. And hauing tried all the <hi>waies</hi> and <hi>baits, and meanes</hi> that I could thinke of, and were allowable for me to <hi>vse</hi> for that purpose, At last I found that <hi>saying</hi> to be true,
<q>
                  <l>Segnius irritant animos, demissa per aures,</l>
                  <l>Quam quae sunt oculis subiecta fidelibus.
<note place="margin">Horat. Art. Poet</note>
                  </l>
               </q> That <hi>ignorant people</hi> are sooner <hi>perswaded</hi> by plaine <hi>simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes</hi> and familiar <hi>examples,</hi> then with <hi>subtill reasons,</hi> and <hi>accurate discourses:</hi> And finding it so, I fell, and set vpon this <hi>worke,</hi> which I call, <hi>A Translation of the Booke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into the vse of Grace.</hi> And here least any man should thinke, that in thus doing, <hi>I attribute</hi> too much to <hi>Naturall reason</hi> and <hi>Philosophie;</hi> as if the points of <hi>Religion</hi> might be sufficiently <hi>proued,</hi> and demonstrated thereby; I shall desire you to doe me that <hi>favour,</hi> as first to <hi>heare</hi> what I <hi>say;</hi> and <hi>see</hi> what I <hi>doe,</hi> and then <hi>Iudge.</hi> For <hi>Philosophie, I</hi> neither alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether seclude her out of the <hi>Church,</hi> as some would doe; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I willingly suffer her to advance her selfe aboue <hi>Divinity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naturalistae.</note> as others would haue. I reverence <hi>Divinity,</hi> as the <hi>Mistres,</hi> I respect <hi>Philosophy,</hi> as the <hi>Hand-maide</hi> to this <hi>Mistres. Moses,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Apostles,</hi> Men of vnquestionable iudgement haue done so: And so I haue ranked them in this <hi>Treatise,</hi> giving <hi>Divinity</hi> the <hi>priority,</hi> to speake in every thinge; and then <hi>Philosophy</hi> the next place, to speake and to <hi>illustrate</hi> the matter. If I had let <hi>naturall reason,</hi> and <hi>Philosophy,</hi> speake in these things alone, then thou mightest iustly <hi>except</hi> against me,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> 1 <hi>part. quaest.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 10.</note> and say with the <hi>Schooleman, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia symbolica non est per se argumentatiua:</hi> Or if I had let <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>Philosophy</hi> speake in the <hi>first place,</hi> I might likewise haue beene iustly <hi>blameable,</hi> for as the <hi>Schoolemen</hi> say well, <hi>Rationes praecedentes minuunt fidem,</hi> reasons going before faith, weaken faith: But inasmuch as I haue made <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> to speake, and to serue in the <hi>second place,</hi> &amp; like a <hi>Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:2"/>to haue alwayes her eyes toward her <hi>Mistres Divinity,</hi> howsoeuer thou iudgest of it, certainely the <hi>Schoolemen</hi> will say, <hi>Rationes subsequentes augent fidem,</hi> that reasons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after faith, doe strengthen faith. <hi>Reason</hi> makes not the matter more sure, <hi>ex parte veritatis dictantis,</hi> in respect of God the speaker: but <hi>ex parte intellectus assentientis,</hi> in respect of the weakenesse of our vnderstanding, which by the acesse of farther knowledge is more confirmed. But these things happly allowed, here againe it may be farther said, that I am too <hi>Copious,</hi> and frequent in this kinde of <hi>argument:</hi> or else ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving set vpon it, that my <hi>Translation</hi> is not so full, and perfect, as it should be. For the <hi>first,</hi> my <hi>frequencie</hi> in this kinde of teaching, the <hi>Hebrew verily</hi> shall speake for me, wherein as the <hi>learned obserue,</hi> almost every word hath a <hi>Metaphoricall sense,</hi> and doth illustrate by some allusion: <hi>imo Haebrei quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis sapienter &amp; subobscurè dictum maximè quod est de ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis siue naturâ, siue officio,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Maschal id est simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem appellant, hoc enim sensu Dicta Salomonis Ethica, quae Proverbia vulgò appellamus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Piscat. in Mat. c. 15.S.</note>
               <hi>nominantur</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mischlé shelomó, id est, parabolae Salomonis.</hi> And for the <hi>second,</hi> I humbly acknowledge it, but yet that shall not <hi>deterre</hi> me from my intended purpose; <hi>Malim enim aliquid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo, majorem à me doctrinam, &amp; sapientiam desiderari, quàm nihil agendo, prudentior, doctiòr{que} judicari:</hi> having receiued a <hi>talent</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi> I know my selfe bound, and that by a straight <hi>charge,</hi> to <hi>negotiate</hi> therewith,
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.13. Mat. 25.27.</note> and to put it to the vttermost <hi>profit,</hi> I had rather then, by doing some good, lay open my infirmities to the censures of men; then by <hi>idlenesse,</hi> to hide my <hi>talent</hi> in the earth, and so to incurre the <hi>indignation</hi> of my <hi>Lord.</hi> Besides if I had prosecuted this <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at this time euer so farre, and euer so exactly, yet I know I should not (no more then my betters) escape the <hi>lash</hi> of <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,</hi> especially of <hi>deficient minds,</hi> and such as knowe, or doe least, whose property is, to seeke by <hi>censuring,</hi> to be accounted <hi>wise,</hi> and to get themselues grace by disgracing of others.</p>
            <p>But howeuer whether by <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>disgrace,</hi> or to vse the words
<pb facs="tcp:177089:3"/>of the <hi>Apostle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. v. 8.</note> Whether by <hi>honour or dishonour, euill report or good report, thus farre I am contented at this time,</hi> to trauell abroad for the common good: And in speciall for your good,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note>
               <hi>little Children, of whome I travell in birth, till Christ be formed in you:</hi> If I find that this my travell likes you, and that any good comes of it, I shall be ready to goe on farther for you in this kinde: In the meane space desiring your acceptance, in way of recompence, <hi>I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, and rest</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, according to my Talent, both to <hi>Preach, and to pray for you. WILLIAM EVANS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:3"/>
            <head>A TRANSLATION OF THE BOOKE OF NATVRE, INTO THE <hi>VSE OF GRACE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. Cap. 12. Ver. 4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>As Wee haue many members in one body, and all members haue not one office: So we being many, are one body in Christ, and every one members one of another.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God in times past diversly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.</note>
               <hi>and many wayes, spake vnto the Fathers by the Prophets:</hi> So also he hath, and doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in <hi>these dayes,</hi> by his <hi>Apostles</hi> &amp; <hi>Ministers.</hi> Speaking and teaching vs sometimes by <hi>plaine principles,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue conclusions,</hi> and otherwhiles by more plaine <hi>parables,</hi> and <hi>simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>this place,</hi> the holy and blessed <hi>Apostle</hi> teacheth vs by a <hi>similitude,</hi> or comparison drawen from the <hi>bodies</hi> of men,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:4"/>saying: <hi>As we haue many members in one body.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the maine thinge which the <hi>Apostle</hi> teacheth vs hereby, is this. Namely that wee should <hi>not bee curious</hi> in searching into hidden thinges, aboue our gifts: or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busie in medling with thinges not pertaining to vs. This appeares by the <hi>precedent,</hi> and <hi>subsequent verses.</hi> For having in the <hi>former verse admonished</hi> every man, <hi>not to thinke of himselfe more highly then he ought to thinke, but to thinke soberly according as God hath dealt to every man, the measure of faith.</hi> And being in the wordes following, to admonish every man to a diligent walking in his owne calling, in these words hee presseth forward his said doctrine, by this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and apt similitude, taken from the bodies of men, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>as we haue many members in one body</hi> &amp;c. Which is as if hee had said thus. As in the body of man, the <hi>members,</hi> though diverse, &amp; of diverse offices, are so <hi>knit together,</hi> that they sweetly agree, without envying, insulting, &amp; incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one vpon another: So ought it to bee in the Church, which is the <hi>Mysticall body</hi> of Christ. This is the scope and meaning of the Apostle in this place.</p>
            <p>And by this we see, we may learne wisdome, as by the <hi>Booke of Grace</hi> the word of God: So by the <hi>Booke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the worke of God. Euen by the <hi>compendium</hi> or <hi>manuell</hi> thereof: Man: specially when these two are ioyned together, &amp; read or heard in their due place and order. The Apostles practise here, is a plaine proofe hereof. And this his practise, <hi>I purpose (God willing)</hi> farther to prosecute, ayming at <hi>one</hi> and the same <hi>end,</hi> which he did, that is, <hi>the speedier edifying of the Church of God.</hi> And the <hi>method</hi> that I shall vse, shall be the very same with the Apostles here. That is, first to propose, and then to demonstrate the said proposall by the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi> And the first proposition shall be. <hi>Quodsit Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>I. That there is A God.</head>
               <p>And <hi>this I say through the grace giuen vnto mee,</hi> to vse the words of the Apostle <hi>vers.</hi> 3. that is by warrant
<pb facs="tcp:177089:4"/>and testimony from the <hi>word of Grace,</hi> committed to my dispensation, being a <hi>Minister,</hi> and namely, by testimonie of those places which say <hi>In the beginning God created the heauen and the earth.</hi> Gen. 1.1. <hi>God created man in his owne Image</hi> vers. 27. <hi>God saw every thinge, that he had made</hi> vers.
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 31. <hi>God spake these words, I am the Lord thy God. God is the king of all the earth. Doubtlesse there is a God</hi> Psal. 58. <hi>vlt.</hi> Thus the Scripture is euident, besides infinite other places, tending to the same purpose.</p>
               <p>And as by the <hi>Booke of Grace,</hi> the Scripture: So by the <hi>Booke of nature, Thy selfe,</hi> thou mayest learne to <hi>beleeue</hi> and <hi>acknowledge. Quod sit Deus,</hi> That there is a God, even by thine <hi>owne conscience accusing</hi> thee for <hi>secret sinnes,</hi> for if thou hast committed any sinne, as Murder, Fornication, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Theft, or the like, &amp; hast done it euer so secretly, and hiddenly from the sight of any person living: yet thine owne conscience will accuse thee, witnesse against thee, trouble thee, and condemne thee for it. Now what doth this accusing, this witnes-bearing, this troubling, terrifying, and condemning of the Conscience meane? But that there is a <hi>spirituall substance, most wise, most holy, most mighty,</hi> that knowes and sees all things, to whome <hi>conscience hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth witnesse,</hi> and whose sentence it stands in feare off, which is neither <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> alone. Not <hi>Man,</hi> for <hi>Man</hi> knoweth not the trespasse committed, whereby the trespasser should stand in feare. And neither <hi>Man,</hi> nor <hi>Angel</hi> can heare the voice of cōscience, or receiue the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony thereof; Or yet discerne what is in the heart of <hi>Man,</hi> whereby he should be disquieted, or troubled in mind. And yet he is troubled, he is vexed, he feareth,
<note place="margin">Si Deus non es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set cur despera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Nero, qui e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectos Dei occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? Cur despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raret Iudas, qui Dominum in manus peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tradidit?</note> yea and sometime despaireth. All which sheweth vndoubtedly that there is a <hi>God. A God</hi> that seeth in secret, that <hi>hateth iniquity,</hi> and will <hi>take vengeance</hi> on them that doe evill. For if there were no God, what need this feare? This trouble and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of conscience for secret sinnes? This doubting, this des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire? Let <hi>Athists</hi> barke against this as long as they will,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:5"/>they haue that in them, that will convince them of the truth of the <hi>God-head,</hi> will they, nill they, either in life, or death. So that they shall say. <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righteous, doubtlesse there is a God that iudgeth the earth.</hi> Psal. 58.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>II. That there is A <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Persons</hi> in the <hi>vnitie</hi> of <hi>Divine essence:</hi>And an <hi>vnitie</hi> of <hi>es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> in the <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Persons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Booke of Grace. There are three that beare record in heauen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.7. Math. 3.16 17. Galatians. 4.9.</note>
                  <hi>The Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost, and these three are one.</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>And this we may learne to acknowledge in some sort, by the <hi>light of Nature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plena Deo similis{que} cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anti. Pruden. de natura animae.</note> even by the <hi>soule</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath giuen vs; <hi>(that sparke of Divinity.)</hi> There are three speciall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or powers of the soule. The <hi>vnderstanding,</hi> the <hi>memory,</hi> and the <hi>will.</hi> And yet these three make but one soule, and this one soule is in these three. In this thou mayest behold some semblance of that great <hi>Mysterie.</hi> And thus <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> doth illustrate the matter. <hi>De Trin. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Idem Epist.</hi> 102. <hi>sic Bernard Meditat. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Et sic alius non infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae sortis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io: Cas: polit. E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pist ad Lect</note>
                  <hi>at{que} eruditionis. Ʋides (inquit ille) in animo tuo tres primas esse potentias, nempe memoriam, intellectum, &amp; voluntatem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In sole etiam babemus quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Tri-vni Dei. Sol patrem, splendor filium, calor spiritum representat.</note>
                  <hi>Ʋides etiam has esse tres distinct as potentias ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi. In super vides has trespotentias vnitas, vnum esse animum in his baptissimae Trinitatis imaginem videas. Nam vt tres potentiae animae, non sunt confusae, sed distinctae: ita quidem sunt tres personae Trinitatis. Sed hae tres potentiae sunt vnus animus: ita &amp; hae tres personae sunt vnus Deus, pernosce ergo te ipsum, Deum{que} trinum &amp; vnum noueris, adcuius similitudinem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus &amp; creatus eras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This similitude I confesse,
<note place="margin">Io: D. serm: of Diuine mist.</note> with a discreet <hi>Moderne Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> doth not so fully illustrate the matter, for if the <hi>Father</hi> begot the <hi>Sonne,</hi> as the <hi>power of the vnderstanding produceth its act,</hi> then must the <hi>Sonne</hi> beget another <hi>Sonne,</hi> as being
<pb facs="tcp:177089:5"/>with the same power indued. Likewise as the spirit is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by loue: so shall it againe produce a spirit by loue; so that this instāce falls short of a due resemblance. And yet this must be granted, that it is the best help &amp; shadow, that either we haue or may expect for expression hereof. Whil'st <hi>Moses</hi> kept <hi>vnvailed,</hi> the <hi>Isralites</hi> could not indure to looke vpon his face, it was so bright; neither may we behold this <hi>Misterie,</hi> vnlesse it be through such shadowes and semblances as these.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="doctrine">
               <head>III. That <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> the Sonne of God is Coeternall with the Father.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>In the beginning was the word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.1.</note>
                  <hi>and the word was with God, and the word was God.</hi> Ioh. 1. v. 1. this is written of Christ. Againe Christ praying vnto his Father saith, <hi>gloryfie thou me with thine owne selfe; with the glory which I had with thee, before the world was.</hi> Ioh. 17.5. <hi>Christ</hi> therefore is <hi>Coeternall</hi> with the Father.</p>
               <p>And for the illustration of this, we haue some helpe from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> Euen from our internall speech or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. For as our internall speech and reason is generated in the soule, and of the soule, and is coetaneall with the soule: So is Christ begotten in the Father and of the Father, and is coeternall with the Father, and therefore hee is called in Scripture <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The word of the Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.1.12.</note> Because (as <hi>Basil</hi> saith) the conception of a word in a mans mind is the neerest thinge,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Basil supra.</hi> 5. Iohan.</note> that in some sort can shadow vnto vs the manner how he is <hi>eternally begotten</hi> of his <hi>Fathers sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="doctrine">
               <head>IIII. That our <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> the Sonne of God,is God and Man in one Person.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Booke of Grace. The word was God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.1. v. 1.4. Gal. 4. v 4 Phillp. 2.</note>
                  <hi>The word was made flesh. Made of a woman. Made man like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:177089:6"/>vs in all things, sinne only excepted.</hi> Yet though he be God and man, he is not two, but one Christ. One person, <hi>one, not by conversion of the God-head into flesh, but by taking of the Man-hood into God. One altogether, not by confusion of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">symbol. Athan.</note>
                  <hi>but by vnity of person.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take some light from <hi>Nature</hi> to cleare this. As the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable <hi>soule</hi> and <hi>flesh</hi> is <hi>one man:</hi> So <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man</hi> is <hi>one Christ.</hi> To this purpose see more. <hi>Calvin. Institut. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. Parag. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="doctrine">
               <head>V. That God in his <hi>Nature</hi> and Attributes is incomprehensible,</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>word of truth. O the depth of the riches both of the wisdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. v. 33.</note>
                  <hi>and knowledge of God, how vnsearchable are his iudgments, and his wayes past finding out.</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>Who is worthy to open the Booke, and to loose the seales of his secrets? There is no man in heauen, nor in earth, neither vnder the earth, that is able to open that booke, neither to looke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, saith an Angel from heauen.</hi> Revel. 5.2.3. <hi>none but the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Tribe of</hi> Iudah. <hi>No man knoweth the Father but the Sonne, and he to whome the Sonne will reveale him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This we may learne to acknowledge even by the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> by that piece thereof, the eye or hand. The eye be it neuer so cleare, cannot see the <hi>thinnesse of the aire:</hi> no more can the <hi>eye of the mind,</hi> truely imbrace the purenesse of the <hi>Deity,</hi> because it wants as it were a solid substance, whereon to fix. The hand cannot graspe a thinge bigger then it selfe: No more can a <hi>finite apprehension,</hi> throughly conceiue the <hi>divine attributes,</hi> being <hi>infinite.</hi> It may well conceiue that they are <hi>infinite,</hi> but not the <hi>infinitenesse; he is as high as heauen, what canst thou doe? Deeper then hell, what canst thou knowe</hi> Iob. 11.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:6"/>
               <head>VI. That the knowledge of God,and of the things of God, is to be learned of God himselfe, in his word.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord in his word <hi>Learne of me.</hi> Mat. 11.24.
<note place="margin">Reuel 3. v 18.</note>
                  <hi>Come and buy from me eye-salue, to annoynt thine eyes, that thou maiest see.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor 2. v. 14.</note>
                  <hi>The naturall man perceaues not the things of the spirit of God. Flesh and blood hath not revealed these things vnto thee: (saith Christ vnto</hi> Peter <hi>vpon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession) but my Father which is in heauen.</hi> Mat. 16.17.
<note place="margin">John. 6.45.</note>
                  <hi>Every man that heard and learned of the Father commeth vnto me</hi> saith Christ. <hi>What man knoweth the things of man saue the spirit of man, which is in him? Euen so the things of God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no man, but the spirit of God, and he to whome the spirit will reveale them.</hi> 1. Cor. 2.11.12.</p>
               <p>Take farther light for the clearing of this from the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> from that part thereof, thine eye, for <hi>sicut sol sine sole non videtur; it a nec Deus sine Deo videri potest.</hi> As the eye though it bee neuer so cleare, cannot see without the light of the Sunne: so our vnderstanding though never so quicke, cannot attaine to know the Lord, vnlesse he by his owne light, reveale himselfe vnto vs in his word. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that the most wise Naturalists, being destitute of this light, <hi>became vaine in their imaginations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note>
                  <hi>and their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish heart was darkned.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="doctrine">
               <head>VII. That the meanes of Salvation is only one,even Christ.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the word of truth.
<note place="margin">Act 4 v. 12.</note>
                  <hi>Neither is there salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any other; for there is none other name vnder heaven giuen among men, whereby we must be saved. To him giue all the Prophets witnesse, that through his name, whosoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in him, should receiue remission of sinne.</hi> Act. 10.45. <hi>In him all the Nations of the Earth are blessed.</hi> Gal. 3 8.
<pb facs="tcp:177089:7"/>
                  <hi>By his only righteousnesse, we are iustified.</hi> Rom. 5.8.</p>
               <p>If we looke into the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> we may find some illustration for this. For as the members of the body, though diverse haue but one meanes of life, even the soule: So Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians though diverse haue but one meanes of saluation, even Christ. And as the members being sicke and readie to dye, are cured, not by their owne power or vertue, but by the helpe of the Physitian, or Chyrurgion: So sinfull soules, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sicke and ready to dye, by reason of sinne, are cured not by their owne power or holynesse,
<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21.</note> but by the help of Christ, the only Physitian of soules, that good Samaritan. <hi>He saueth his people from their sinnes. And beside him, there is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> Isa. 43.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="doctrine">
               <head>VIII. That we must haue a sense,and a sorrow for our sinnes, before we can be saued by Christ.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>Come vnto me all yee that are wearie &amp; heauie laden, &amp; I will refresh you. Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Before we</hi> can looke for ease &amp; refreshing at Christs hands, we must be sensible of the heauie burden of our sinnes, &amp; be wearie of it &amp; willing &amp; desirous to be eased of it. Come vnto me yee that are wearie, <hi>saith Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this we may <hi>learne</hi> to perswade our selues of, if we obserue but the course of <hi>Nature.</hi> For if a man carrie a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burden, too <hi>heauie</hi> for him to <hi>beare,</hi> he is not <hi>like to be eased,</hi> till being sensible of the <hi>weight</hi> thereof, he <hi>complaine</hi> and call for helpe, to some friend or other: And no more are we, being <hi>heauie laden</hi> with the burden of sinne, (as we are all by nature (like to finde ease, and helpe, at the hands of <hi>Christ,</hi> till hauing a sensible feeling, of the heauie weight and burden thereof, lying vpon our soules, we come, and call vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for helpe, for then, and not vntill then, is his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of refreshing made.
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> affords more similies, for the illustrating of this <hi>truth.</hi> And because it is a thing worthie to be remembred, I
<pb facs="tcp:177089:7"/>will produce one more, and that shall be of a sicke man. If a man bee sicke, and sore displeased, hee is not like to finde helpe and health, till hauing a feeling of his paine, hee complaine of his griefe, and let the Phisitian knowe where his paine lies, &amp; desires his helpe: And no more is any man (being sicke in soule, by reason of sinne) like to be cured by Christ till hauing a feeling of his spirituall infirmitie, he complaine of the griefe &amp; paine thereof, &amp; open &amp; declare his sinfull and damnable estate, and desire for helpe. Christ saith that he Came not to call the righteous, <hi>but sinners to repentance.</hi> Not the righteous, that is, not those who thinke themselues in a right good estate of themselues, by vertue of their owne righteousnesse, having no sight nor sense of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wants they haue. But he Came to call <hi>sinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that is, those that haue a sense, and feeling of their sinnes, and are sorie for them, that haue such a sense, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their owne sinnes, and vnrighteousnesse, as that they <hi>hunger and thirst after the righteousnesse of Christ,</hi> that they may be found in it. <hi>These meeke ones, these humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hearts</hi> Christ came to call, to saue, and not the proud ones, not those who are <hi>pure in their owne eyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 50. v. 12.</note>
                  <hi>and yet are not washed from their sinnes,</hi> not those who are soule-sicke of sinne, and yet thinke themselues well. He that is sicke,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quid miserius misero non mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reante seipsum. Augusti Confes. lib</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 13.</note> and feeles no paine, but thinks himselfe well, is in a very ill ease, saith the Physitian. A case, a great deale worse then his, who is sicke, and sensible of his disease: And verily so is he, who is soule-sicke by reason of his sinne, (as we are all more or lesse) and yet is not touched with a feeling thereof. Such a one is in a desperate case. For <hi>primus ad sanitatem gradus est novisse morbum.</hi> We are neuer in the way to obtaine health, either of body, or of soule, till we knowe and are sensible of our disease, either spirituall, or corporall, sinne or sicknesse.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:8"/>
               <head>IX. That we must consider our wayes,and take notice of our sinnes and misery, before we can truely repent, and turne to God.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Booke of Grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.5.</note>
                  <hi>Let vs search and trie our wayes, and turne againe to the Lord.</hi> Lament. 3, 40. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from whence thou art fallen, and repent. Thus did</hi> David. <hi>I considered my wayes</hi> (saith he,) <hi>and turned my feete vnto thy Testimonies</hi> Psal. 119.54.</p>
               <p>And this we may learne to acknowledge by the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> Even by the sense of seeing, for <hi>that which the eye seeth not, the heart rueth not.</hi> There is no sorrow for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne sinne, and vnknowne danger: As long as a man doth not consider his wayes, and take notice of his sinfull and miserable estate,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.</note> hee thinks all is well, as the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> did, he hath no remorse for any thinge that he did. But once beholding, &amp; throughly viewing his sinfull wayes, and danger thereby, repentance followes, as we may see in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who hauing thought of his wayes, <hi>turned his feete vnto Gods Testimonies.</hi> And in <hi>Peter,</hi> who having remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred how he had shamefully denied his Master, <hi>went forth and wept bitterly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 26</note> Thus serious consideration brings forth serious humiliation, serious conversion vnto God. We see in <hi>Nature</hi> there is the same instrument of seeing, and of weeping; to shew that weeping depends vpon seeing, hee that sees well,
<note place="margin">psal 38 v. 18.</note> weepes well, he that sees his sinnes thorowly, will be waile them heartily. I say then with the Prophet, <hi>stand in awe and sinne not. Commune with your owne hearts in your Chamber, and be still.</hi> Psal. 4, 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="doctrine">
               <head>X. That Confession of sinnes brings peace to the Soule,and quietnesse to the Heart.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the holy Prophet;
<note place="margin">psal. 32. v. 234.5.6.</note> in the <hi>Booke of Grace. While I held my tongue,</hi> that is, not confessing my sinnes, <hi>my bones
<pb facs="tcp:177089:8"/>consumed away through my daily complaining. For thy hand was heauy vpon me day and night, and my moysture like the drought in summer. But I said I will confesse my sinne, and so thou forgauest the iniquity of my sinne, thou didest free mee from trouble, and compasse me about with songs of deliuerance.</hi> v. 7. Thus confession of his sinnes brought ease to his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And so still <hi>he that covereth his sinnes, shall not prosper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov 28 v 13</note> but he that <hi>confesseth and forsaketh them, shall haue mercy, shall haue ease in his minde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this we may learne to acknowledge out of the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> even by the easing of a sicke stomacke.
<note place="margin">Quicquid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiae stoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum grauat, totum vomitu purae confessio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Euomerene differas. Bern.</note> For as a sicke stomacke is eased by vomiting. So is a guilty conscience eased by confession, and not before. Deferre not then to take this vomit, if thou wilt haue ease and quietnesse of minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="doctrine">
               <head>XI. That we should not be deiected in minde,or cast away our hope, by reason of troubles of minde, streights of conscience, or vexation of spirit.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>word of Grace. The sacrifice of God is a troubled spirit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal 51.17.</note>
                  <hi>A broken &amp; contrite heart O God thou wilt not despise.</hi> This <hi>Dauid</hi> knew,
<note place="margin">Psal. 42. v. 5.</note> and therefore in the troubles of his minde, he encourageth his <hi>soule,</hi> and saith. <hi>Why art thou Cast downe, O my soule, and why art thou so disquieted within me? hope thou still in God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And verily if we looke into the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> we may obserue &amp; gather somewhat to cleere this matter, and that by the manner of the naturall birth: for as there can bee no birth without the paines of Trauell going before: So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can our new birth be wrought without godly sorrow, and anguish of spirit. The sorrowes of a woman in Trauell are the fore-runners of a naturall birth: and so the sanctified troubles of conscience are but the dolours of the New birth. And therefore in such perplexity, comfort thy selfe, and say with the holy Prophet. <hi>Why art thou so disquieted, O my soule, and why art thou so vexed within me? Hope thou still in
<pb facs="tcp:177089:9"/>the Lord.</hi> Psalme. 42.5.11.43.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="doctrine">
               <head>XII. That the soule is immortall.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>word of Grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.25.26.</note>
                  <hi>He that beleeueth though he were dead, yet shall he liue. When the body returnes to the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclesi. 12. v. 7.</note>
                  <hi>the spirit returneth to God that gaue it. When all turne to dust both man, and beast, the spirit of man goeth vpward, and the spirit of the beast goeth downeward.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclesi 3. v. 21.</note>
                  <hi>When the body is dead because of sinne, the spirit is life for righteousnesse sake.</hi> Rom. 8.10.</p>
               <p>And this doth appeare likewise by the <hi>light of Nature,</hi> even by the motions of the soule,
<note place="margin">Sir Ioh: Douis in his noscete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipsum.</note> and the affections thereof, as the desire of death in the better, and the feare of death in the worser sort of soules, take the forme of argument here hence in his words and forme, who hath many more to this purpose.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reason drawne from the motion of the soule.</note> How can shee but immortall be?</l>
                     <l>When with the motions of wit and will,</l>
                     <l>Shee still aspireth to eternity?</l>
                     <l>And neuer rests; till she attaine to it?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Water in Conduit-pipes can rise no higher</l>
                     <l>Then the well-head, from whence it first doth spring,</l>
                     <l>Then since to the eternall God she doth aspire,</l>
                     <l>She cannot be, but an eternall thing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reason. from Contempt of death in the better sort of spirits.</note> The better Soules doe oft despise</l>
                     <l>The bodies death, and doe it oft desire:</l>
                     <l>For when on ground the burthened ballance lyes,</l>
                     <l>The empty part is lifted vp the higher.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if the bodies death the soule should kill,</l>
                     <l>Then death must needs against her nature be;</l>
                     <l>And were it so, all soules would fly it still,</l>
                     <l>For Nature hates and shunnes her contrary.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177089:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For all things else, which Nature makes to be,</l>
                     <l>Their being to preserue, are chiefly taught;</l>
                     <l>For though some things desire a change to see,</l>
                     <l>Yet neuer thinge did long to turne to nought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If then the soule were quenched quite,</l>
                     <l>She could not thus against her Nature runne;</l>
                     <l>Since every senslesse thinge by Natures light</l>
                     <l>Doth preservation seeke, destruction shunne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reason from the feare of death, in the wicked soules.</note> And as the better spirit, when she doth beare</l>
                     <l>Ascorne of death, doth shew she cannot dye;</l>
                     <l>So when the wicked soule deaths face doth feare,</l>
                     <l>Even then she proues her owne Eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For when deaths forme appeares, she feareth not</l>
                     <l>An vtter quenching, or extinguishment;</l>
                     <l>She would be glad to meet with such a lot,</l>
                     <l>That so she might all future ill prevent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But she doth doubt what after may befall;</l>
                     <l>For Natures law accuseth her within,</l>
                     <l>And saith, tis true, that is affirm'd by all,</l>
                     <l>That after death, there is a paine for sinne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="doctrine">
               <head>XIII. That there shall be a resurrection of the body.</head>
               <p>This the <hi>Booke of Grace</hi> testifieth saying.
<note place="margin">Job. 19.26.27</note>
                  <hi>Thy Dead shall liue,</hi> Esay. 26.19. <hi>the houre commeth in which all that are in the graue, shall heare the voyce of the Sonne of Man, and shall come forth.</hi> Ioh. 5.25.28.29.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 37.5.</note>
                  <hi>This corruptible must put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.53. <hi>Thou wilt not leaue my soule in hell, neither wilt thou suffer thy holy one to see corruption.</hi> Psal. 16. v. 10.</p>
               <p>With this agreeth the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> we see, &amp; know, the body cannot sinke, or be drowned, as long as the head is
<pb facs="tcp:177089:10"/>aboue water. Now Christ is our head, and we are his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, our head is risen, and holds vp, and is <hi>exalted farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all heauens.</hi> We shall not then beleft behind, but even this body shall be receaued into heauen,
<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> whether he hath carryed the pledge of it, in his humanity. Be secure O flesh and blood, thou vsurpest heauen in thy head Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="doctrine">
               <head>XIIII. The Salvation of those which truely repent, and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly beleeue the holy Gospell,is sure and certaine,</head>
               <p>This the <hi>Words of Grace</hi> witnesseth, saying, <hi>Whosoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in the Sonne of God, shall not perish, but haue ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life.</hi> Ioh. 3.16. <hi>there is no condemnation to them that are in Christ Iesus, which walke not after the flesh, but after the spirit.</hi> Rom. 8.1. <hi>the gates of hell shall not prevaile against them.</hi> Mat. 16.18. <hi>God willing more abundantly, to shew vnto the heires of promise the immutability of his counsell, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it by an Oath, that we might haue a strong consolation.</hi> Heb. 16.17.18.</p>
               <p>This assurance, <hi>the Booke of Nature</hi> doth in some sort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate vnto vs. We see, if the head liue, the body liues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. in Rom.</hi> 5.10.</note> for the head liues not without the body. Now Christ our head is aliue, and aliue for evermore. <hi>Death hath no more dominion ouer him.</hi> If Christ then liue, we shall liue, being knit, and vnited vnto him by faith. Yea with reverence be it spoken, Christ must cease to be himselfe, if we be not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, we that truely repent, and vnfainedly beleeue the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, neither can he be saued (in the integrity of his body the Church) without vs, as the head liues not without the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:10"/>
               <head>XV. That no man vpon the hearing of
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25.34 Ephes 1.4. Eccles. 3.14</note> Gods eternall Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vnchangable decree, is to cast away the care of a good life, saying, If I be Predestinated to be saued, I shall be saued, let me liue as I list; and if I be Predestinated to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I shall bee damned, let me doe what I can.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>This wisdome is not from aboue but is earthly, sensuall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.15.</note>
                  <hi>and divelish.</hi> The wisdome which is from aboue, saith, that <hi>whome God hath predestinated to salvation</hi> hereafter, them he <hi>predestinateth to be conformed to the image of his Sonne here.</hi> As first to be <hi>called,</hi> then <hi>iustified,</hi> after <hi>sanctified,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 29.30.</note> and last of all to be <hi>glorified.</hi> Rom. 8. v. 29.30. <hi>They who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected according to the fore-knowledge of God the Father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to salvation; are elect also,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2.</note>
                  <hi>through the sunctification of the spirit vnto obedience</hi> 1. Pet. 1.2. Though glorification doe necessarily follow predestination, or election,
<note place="margin">praedestinatio non facit saltum</note> yet not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly; there are meanes and wayes from the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen <hi>the way of good workes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 2. v. 10.</note>
                  <hi>which God hath ordained that we should walke in them.</hi> Doe not then neglect the way of good workes, the way of a Godly conversation, because of the immutability of Gods purpose.</p>
               <p>Learne better wisdome then that from the <hi>Booke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> For put the case, that thou wert on the top of an high Tower: and that God hath Predestinated, that thou shalt come safely downe, or else breake thy Neck in comming downe: wilt thou now leap downe vpon this reason, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the ordinary way? I trow not, thou wilt not trust thy body vpon these termes. And art thou so madde as to trust thy soule on such. Say farther that God hath predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated that thou shalt liue to the end of this present day, or that thou shalt dye before night; wilt thou vpon this drinke poyson, saying why, If God hath predestinated I shall liue, I shall liue, though I eate poyson. If to dye, then I shall dye,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:11"/>though I be neuer so carefull. If thou beest in thy right minde,
<note place="margin">Esay. 38. v. 5.</note> thou wilt not doe thus. <hi>Hezekia</hi> had assurance of the prolonging of his life, for fifteene yeeres, yet neglected not the meanes of preseruing his life. So the predestination of God, ought not to make vs carelesse of vsing the meanes of saluation, but knowing that God hath decreed to saue by meanes, we should vse the meanes to make our calling and election sure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="doctrine">
               <head>XVI. That God is not the Author of sinne.</head>
               <p>This the <hi>Booke of Grace</hi> witnesseth, saying. <hi>Let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God: for God cannot be tempted with evill, neither tempteth he any man, to wit, vnto sinne.</hi> Iam. c. 1.13. <hi>God hath no pleasure in wickednesse, neither shall any evill dwell with him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wild cap. 15.11.12.</note> Psal. 5 4. <hi>the Lord loueth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and hateth iniquity.</hi> Psal. 45. <hi>he hath no need of the sinfull man.</hi> It is true, God is the author of every action of man, <hi>for in him we liue, moue, and haue our being.</hi> Act. 17. but not of the <hi>ataxie,</hi> or disorder, that is in the action, not of the prauity of it. <hi>The doing of a thinge proceedeth from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</hi> 2. Sam. 24. <hi>But the evill doing of it commeth from the Creature.</hi> Ier. 13.23. Hosea. 12.</p>
               <p>Take some light from the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> for the farther manifestation of this point. In the generation of an Infant, the Sunne and Man doe concurre together,
<note place="margin">Sol &amp; homo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> yet if a Monster be generated, it is not ascribed to the Sunne, but to man; for therefore is the Monster bred, because through the defect of the Organ, or the euill affection of the matter, the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall agent cause is withdrawne from the accustomed Course: Euen so to humane actions, God and man doe concurre, yet if any euill be in the action, it ought not to be ascribed to God, but to the euill disposition of mans will: The diuell, or man that entiseth another, or a mans owne selfe, that enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth himselfe are the true causes and authors of sinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:11"/>
               <head>XVII. Not to be questioning of hidden things,or of those things which are not profitable to knowe.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Booke of Grace: Secret things belong vnto God, but things revealed to vs, and our Children.</hi> Deut. 29. vlt.
<note place="margin">Psal. 147. v. 5.</note>
                  <hi>That which is farre off, and exceeding deepe, who can finde it out?</hi> Ecclesi. 2.24. <hi>and now Gods Iudgments are like a great deepe.</hi> Psal. 36.6 <hi>his wisedome is infinite. There is no searching of his vnderstanding.</hi> Esay. 40.28. <hi>his iudgments are vnsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and his wayes past finding out.</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>Seeke not out then the things that are too hard for thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 3 v. 21.22.23.</note>
                  <hi>neither search the things that are aboue thy strength, but what is commanded thee, thinke therevpon with reverence, for it is not needfull for thee to see with thine eyes, the things that are in secret, be not curious in vnnecessary matters.</hi> Ecclesi. 3.</p>
               <p>Learne better wisedome then this,
<note place="margin">Pius pulsator plerumq inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, quod teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius scrutator inuenire non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, Bern.</note> from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> Thou knowest that to stare earnestly vpon the Sunne, is the way to loose our sight, not to increase it, not to see more, but not to see at all: so the way to vnderstand, and to attaine wisedome, is not to be busie in searching but to content our selues, with that which is revealed. Nay to presse divine Mysteries too hard, is the way to become ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious vnto errours, and slips: for as the stomacke when it meeteth with meat hard, and not easie to be digested, sends vp noxious vapours into the braine: Euen so we lighting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on points which are to knottie for vs, and not being gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by discretion, insteed of doctrines broach our wild conceits. But are there any points of divine Mysteries so knottie, and difficult, which a deep Scholler, a studious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, an illuminated spirit cannot find out? Yes, very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as <hi>the obscurity of the Trinity and vnity. The</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Luk 1.35.</note>
                  <hi>personall vnion of the two Natures in Christ: The Mysticall vnion of Christ and his Church. The reiection of the Iewes, and the calling of the Gentiles, and the recalling of the Iewes, The</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 11 33</note>
                  <hi>depth of predestination, the manner of regeneration.</hi> Ioh. 3.8.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:12"/>
               <p>All these are vnsearchable, past finding out to the full, by the most illuminated spirits that liue, for they that haue abundance of revelations,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 1. Cor. 8.2.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> had. They that knowe most, yet <hi>knowe but in part,</hi> yea <hi>they knowe nothing as they ought to knowe.</hi> Now they <hi>see but through a glasse darklie.</hi> v. 12.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. v. 12.</note> the full fight, and perfect knowledge of these high and sublime Mysteries, is not for the life temporall, but for the eternall,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3. 1. Cor. 13.12. Ela. 40 13. Rom. 11, 34. Wisdome. 9.13.</note> so it is written. <hi>This is life eternall to knowe God. Then we shall see God face to face; then we shall knowe even as wee are knowne.</hi> Let it bee our wisdome then, to see and acknowledge our want of wisdome, to comprehend these deepe Mysteries of God and let vs not take vpon vs (be we ever so learned) to speake too freely or peremptorily, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitiuely of them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.22. Tim. 6.4.</note>
                  <hi>as if we had knowne the minde of the Lord herein, or had beene his Counsellours.</hi> Rather let vs religiously adore these things by faith, then curiously search into them by reason farther then Gods word doth allow. Let vs make them rather matter to admire at, not so much to inquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, least
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quando anima cogitationum vincitur frebre &amp;c tunc que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, cum vero sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na est, nō querit sed fideliter cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Chrys. hom.</hi> in Cap 11. Epist. ad Rom v. 33.</note>
                  <hi>in professing to be wise, we proue our selues foolish;</hi> and <hi>sicke</hi> rather then <hi>sound.</hi> For as <hi>sicke stomacks</hi> long for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thinge they heare of, and when they haue it, they can take no profit by it: So it is an argument of a weake minde, to be questioning of that which to knowe, would not bee profitable. When the minde is sicke, then it is questioning. Why? How? Wherefore? But when it is sound, then it questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth not, but beleeueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="doctrine">
               <head>XVIII. That we are to ascribe the praise and glory of all the good,that we thinke, speake, or doe, to the goodnesse, and grace of God, &amp; not to our owne good Nature.</head>
               <p>This the <hi>Booke of Grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 9.23. 1. Cor. 1.31.</note> doth frequently put vs in minde, <hi>he that gloryeth, let him glory in the Lord,</hi> saith the Prophet,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> and the Apostle, <hi>we are not sufficient of our selues, to thinke any thinge as of our selues: but our sufficiencie</hi> is of God saith the same Apostle. <hi>The Lord worketh all our workes in vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Esa. 26.12.</note> saith the Prophet <hi>Esay.</hi> Therefore, <hi>Not vnto vs O Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:12"/>not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the praise,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Esa 26.12. Psal. 115.1.</note> saith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> is teady to teach vs. Wee see in <hi>Nature</hi> the members of the body, not being made by their owne vertue; but created by Gods almighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before they execute their function, or office: So we that are Christians, are not members of Christ, through our owne workes, but we doe good workes being first members, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted into Christ. <hi>Without him we can doe nothing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5. Philip. 4. v. 13. Ioh. 1.13. Iams. 1.18.</note>
                  <hi>Through him we are able to doe all things. Without him we are dead in trespasses &amp; sinnes.</hi> Ephes. 2.1. <hi>(and what can a dead man doe to his owne quickning?) through him we are aliue vnto God.</hi> Rom. 6.11. <hi>Without him we are not borne anew, and what can a mā doe before he is borne? By him</hi> regeniti sumus, <hi>we are begotten anew. Without him we are carnall, sold vnder sinne, in captiuity to the law of sinne. Through him we are made free;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.1.23. Ioh. 8.36 Rom. 8.1.</note>
                  <hi>free from the service and bondage of sinne.</hi> Rom. 12.14.22. <hi>free from the eternall condemnation of sinne.</hi> Free and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to forsake all kinde of sinne, and to will, and to doe that which is good. <hi>If the Sonne doe make vs free, then are we free indeed.</hi> Ioh. 8.36. Not vnto thy selfe then, <hi>O man,</hi> not vnto thy selfe, or to any other Creature, giue the glory; but to thy mercifull Creator and redeemer the Lord Iesus,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note>
                  <hi>of whom, and through whom are all things, to whom be glory for euer Amen.</hi> 1. Cor. 8.6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="doctrine">
               <head>XIX. That we are to raise our affections from earthly things,and to set them on things that are aboue.</head>
               <p>This <hi>Grace</hi> doth greatly exhort vnto.
<note place="margin">Colos. 3. v. 1 2</note>
                  <hi>If yee be risen with Christ,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>seeke those things that are aboue, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God. Set your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on things that are aboue, not on things on earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6.19.20. Ioh. 6.27.</note>
                  <hi>Lay not vp for your selues treasure vpon earth saith Christ &amp;c. But lay vp for your selues treasure in heauen. Labour not for the meat that perisheth, but for that which endureth to euerlasting
<pb facs="tcp:177089:13"/>life.</hi> S. Paul <hi>did suffer the losse of all things, and did count them but dung that he might winne Christ, and be found in him.</hi> This one thinge he did aboue all;
<note place="margin">Philip. 3. v. 8.9.13.14.</note> even presse hard toward this marke; the marke of the high calling in Christ Iesus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs as many as be perfect, be so minded.</hi> And for a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inducement herevnto, hearken and consider what the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> hath to this purpose.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid. met.</note> Os homini sublime dedit, Coelum{que} tueri</l>
                  <l>Iussit, &amp; erectos ad sider a tollere vultus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Whereas all <hi>other Creatures</hi> are made to goe with their bodyes and eyes to the ground ward,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Columb lib</hi> 5 <hi>c</hi> 9.</note> man was made to goe vpright, and whereas all other Creatures haue but foure muscles, to turne their eyes round about, man hath a fift to lift his eyes vp to heauen ward. Now what doth this inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate vnto vs? But that, howsoeuer we seeke for other things, yet first of all, and aboue all, we <hi>should seeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and the righteousnesse thereof,</hi> and set our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall desires, to enioy that blessed state of Gods children in heauen. But is it so in the practise of men? Most men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed goe vpright but looke into their liues, and they might as well goe on all foure: for in their owne Conuersations they set their whole hearts vpon the earth, as the beast doth, and their eyes vpon the things of this world; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they doe abase themselues, and deface their bodyes, and being men, make themselues as beasts. We shall see great numbers of men, that runne and ride from place to place, to prouide for the body but to seeke the kingdome of God, where their soules should dwell after this life, in ioy for euer, they will not stirre one foote. But remember thy selfe, <hi>O man,</hi> and consider, that God hath giuen thee a sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a countenance, aspiring vpward, not groueling like a beast toward the earth, and this to the end that thou shouldst learne hereby to set thy affections on things aboue, and not on things on earth, And moreouer he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed thine eyes with browes, and lids, and fences from dust and earth, that though thou lookest sometimes on earth, yet
<pb facs="tcp:177089:13"/>the least dust, or earth should not get into them. Againe Consider that God hath made man with his feet to tread vpon the earth; as with his face to looke to heauen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to teach vs, to spurne at, and to contemne the world, in respect of heauen and heauenly things, and not to delight much in those things, by which the earth may be gained, but rather in those things, by which the great &amp; excellent glory of heauen may be obtained. This the Lord doth farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and set forth vnto vs, by a great wonder, or signe from heauen, in the 12 of the Reuelation. v. 1. Where the Church is described vnto vs, hauing the <hi>sunne,</hi> and the <hi>twelue starres</hi> on her head, and the <hi>moone</hi> vnder her feete. By the <hi>sunne,</hi> and the <hi>twelue starres,</hi> is meant <hi>Christ,</hi> and the doctrine of the twelue Apostles, which is, as a diadem of beautie to her head and by the Moone vnder her feete, is figured the mutable world. Now seeing God hath set downe this order, that we should tread vpon the earth, hauing Christ, and his word on our heads. It is a shame to alter this order, as carnall men doe, who tread Christ and his word vnder their feete; and put the world as a garland vpon their <hi>heads.</hi> But the Good Christian will neuer place that nigh his heart, nor vpon his head, which God hath placed vnder his feete.</p>
               <p>And no more, would any man doe, if he did but note and obserue that doctrine, which the very frame and forme of his heart doth continually teach him, which is thus. Mans heart is made broad aboue, narrow beneath. Open at the top, close below. To signifie that we should inlarge our affections towards heauenly things: And draw them to as narrow a point, as possibly we can, concerning earth, and earthly things: And so by the fashion of our hearts, we may learne not to follow the fashion of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="doctrine">
               <head>XX. That the things of this world are not satisfactory,or able to fill and content the minde of man.</head>
               <p>This the <hi>word of Grace</hi> doth plainely and frequently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb facs="tcp:177089:14"/>and witnesse vnto vs, saying <hi>The eye cannot be satisfied with seeing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.13.</note>
                  <hi>nor the eare with hearing. All things haue an emptinesse and extreame vanity. He that loueth siluer shall not be satisfied with siluer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. 5.10.</note>
                  <hi>nor he that loueth abundance with increase. Whosoeuer drinketh of this water shall thirst againe, saith Christ himselfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quo plus sunt potae plus sitiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aquae,</note> There is a defect in the water of <hi>Iacobs</hi> well, and in euery other earthly thing whatsoeuer; as that it cannot satisfie the soule, or Conferre any true Contentment to the mind.</p>
               <p>This we may learne likewise to acknowledge, out of the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> and namely out of that middle part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the heart, the heart of man is made like a triangle, and the world round as a Circle. Now a Circle cannot fill a triangle, but there will be some comer empty. The whole Circular world cānot fill the triangular heart of man. It must be a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> that can replenish this triangle. And there is no other <hi>Trinitie</hi> that can doe it, but the <hi>holy, blessed, &amp; glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> the father, sonne, and holy ghost. When <hi>God the father,</hi> the most ancient of dayes, shall fill our <hi>memory;</hi> God the sonne, who is wisdom it selfe, shall fill <hi>our vnderstanding:</hi> God the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> who is contentation and loue, shall sit in our will,
<note place="margin">Ceteris rebus eccupari potest, repleri non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Bern.</note> then all the powers of our mind will be at rest, when as they shall enioy him who made them. Then the mind will be satisfied, and contented, and not till then.</p>
               <p>There is nothing that takes any perfect rest or content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in his proper obiect or Center. We know if a man had all the musicke, &amp; melody in the world before him, he could not heare it with his <hi>eyes,</hi> because it is the <hi>proper obiect</hi> of the eare, if neuer so gorgious shewes, he Could not see them with his eares, because it is the proper obiect of the eye: So it is with the soule of man; if it were possible that all the treasures, pleasures, honours, preferments and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, which the world doth afford, were presented, and tendered to this Soule, yet would they not afford vnto it any perfect satisfaction, because they be not the Proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and Center of the soule. The proper obiect and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:177089:14"/>of the soule, is the Lord himselfe.
<note place="margin">fecisti nos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine propter le, &amp; semper in quietum est Cor nostrum, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec requiescat in to, August.</note> And therefore we may say, as a father hath excelently said. Thou hast made vs O Lord for thy selfe, and our heart is euen vnquiet till it rest in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simile nutritur simili, ex ijsdem nutrimur, ex quibus su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Each thinge is fed, nourished and satisfied with food of like substance vnto it selfe, as earthly things are fed with earthly and corporall food. Now the soule is spirituall, and the foode that it must haue, must be of like substance vnto it selfe, spirituall, not earthly and corporall; it is as impossible to replenish a spirituall emptinesse, with a corporall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, the minde of man with earthly treasures, as it is to fill a corporall emptinesse, with a spirituall substance, as a house with vertues, or the stomacke with wisedome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXI. That we ought to endeavour to grow every day better and better, and to increase in Grace.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Booke of Grace, Grow vp in him who is the head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 15.</note>
                  <hi>Christ Iesus; Grow vp vnto true holynesse in the feare of God.</hi> 1. Cor. 7.1. <hi>increase more and more</hi> 1 Thes. 4.10. <hi>Giue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to adde to your faith, vertue, and to vertue knowledge, and to knowledge, temperance, and to temperance, patience, and to patience, godlynesse, and to godlynesse, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and to brotherly kindnesse, charitie.</hi> 2. per. 1.5.6.7. <hi>Be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abounding in the works of the Lord.</hi> 1. Cor. 15. vlt.
<note place="margin">Colos. 1.10. c. 2.2.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This we may learne in some sort out of the <hi>Booke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> In our walking, there seemes to be an emulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the feet, to be one before another: so in our living and spirituall walking, we must striue to be every day more forward in goodnesse, and to be better to morrow, then we are to day. After conception the Infant stirres, and growes more strong every day then other: So it is in the spirituall birth. It is thought strange to see a man of many yeares, who yet in stature, strength, and wit, went neuer beyond the measure of a Child; such a one is counted for a Monster:
<pb facs="tcp:177089:15"/>And truely no better is the carelesse Christian, who after so many yeares profession, growes not in grace, nor knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but still remaines a child in vnderstanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXII. That we doe not liue the life of Grace,vnlesse we be actiue and stirring in good motions, and godly actions; desirous and diligent in seeking the sincere milke of Gods word, the foode thereof; sensible of our owne corruptions, and whatsoeuer is an enemy vnto it and carefull to resist it.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Booke of Grace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12. v. 5. Gal. 5.25.</note>
                  <hi>They that be after the spirit, doe minde the things of the spirit, doe walke after the spirit, desire the sincere milke of the word that they may growe thereby.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Psal. 1.2.</note> Pet. 2.2. <hi>Delight in the law of the Lord and therein exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise themselues both day and night, are sensible of the law in their members, warring against the law of their minde.</hi> Rom. 7.23. Complaine of the opposition thereof, saying <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am, who shall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> v. 24. <hi>striue &amp; fight against it with all their force,</hi> Gal. 5.17. Thus it is with them that liue the life of <hi>Grace,</hi> by graces teaching.</p>
               <p>And this we may learne to acknowledge by the <hi>light of Nature.</hi> Where there is <hi>Naturall life,</hi> there is <hi>motion</hi> and stirring, the pulse beating more or lesse, life is not without some motion, but is actiue &amp; euer doing: So, where there is any <hi>life of grace,</hi> there will be spirituall motions, &amp; a liuelines to spirituall exercises, as to pray, to praise God, to read his word, to heare it, to meditate and conferre of it, to obserue &amp; keepe it. And so spirituall life will expresse it selfe, by spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall motions, and <hi>the life of grace, by grace in the life. If we liue then in the spirit, let vs walke in the spirit</hi> Gal. 5.25.</p>
               <p>Againe, life will euer seeke its owne preseruation. The li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ttle infant so soone as he is borne Cryes for helpe, and seeks
<pb facs="tcp:177089:15"/>after the brest. So it is with such as liue the life of grace, they hunger and thirst for the food of their soules, and <hi>as new borne babes desire the sincere milke of the word, that they may grow thereby;</hi> as Saint peter teacheth vs, 1. Pet. 22. A liuely Child desires Sometimes to sucke of both his mothers brests, and so doth the Child of God desire and thirst some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to sucke the <hi>two brests</hi> of his <hi>mother</hi> the Church, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the <hi>two Testaments,</hi> till he hath drawne spirituall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment, strength of faith, and increase of grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence.</p>
               <p>He that liues the life of Nature, doth not onely seeke his owne preseruation, but seekes it dayly, constantly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, so long as he hath any being. The <hi>young infant</hi> doth almost nothing else but sucke, and sleepe, and then Cry for the brest againe: Thus it is with them that liue the <hi>life of grace;</hi> there is a dayly seeking after food for the preseruing of it; a dayly vsing of the meanes, as prayer, reading, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the like. So the holy prophet testifieth of the blessed man, saying, that <hi>in Gods law, he doth exercise himselfe day and night,</hi> Psal 1.2.</p>
               <p>He that liues the life of <hi>Nature,</hi> is <hi>sensible</hi> of whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is an enemie vnto it, and doth resist it, he is sensible of euery disease, and maladie, if his tooth, or finger doe but ake, he presently feels it, and striues against it: Thus it is with such as liue the <hi>life of grace,</hi> they <hi>feele</hi> their corruptions, and striue against them. They feele their vnbeleefe opposing their faith, their dulnesse and deadnesse opposing their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Gods seruice, the sinfull lusts of their flesh, warring against the spirituall motions of the spirit, the working of sinne opposing the light of grace, this they are sensible off, and struggle, and striue against it. <hi>The spirit fighteth against the flesh,</hi> Gal. 5.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:16"/>
               <head>XXIII. That we cannot liue the life of grace,except we attend vpon the word of Grace, the holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Apostle,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note>
                  <hi>we are borne againe, not of Corrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible seed, but of incorruptible euen by the word of God, which liueth and abideth for euer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.18.</note> Againe, <hi>of his owne will begat he vs, with the word of truth.</hi> Farther, <hi>we liue by the faith of the sonne of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20. Rom. 10.</note>
                  <hi>this faith Comes by hearing, hearing by the word of God.</hi> So that the word of God is the seed of our new birth. And being so, we cannot be borne a new, much lesse liue a new life without it.</p>
               <p>This Nature will shadow vnto vs. We see, to a <hi>Naturall life,</hi> there must be a generation according to the flesh: it is so, in the <hi>spirituall life</hi> if thou would'st attaine to it, thou must of necessitie be begot, not of mortall, but of the <hi>immortall seed</hi> of Gods word, 1 Pet 1.23. So then if thou desirest to liue this life, be frequent in hearing of the word. <hi>For the dead shall heare his voice, and they that heare, shall liue</hi> Ioh. 5.25.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXIIII. That we must take heed of omitting that good which we should doe;as well as of committing that euill which we should not doe, if we desire to saue, and not to loose our soules.</head>
               <p>Thus the word of truth.
<note place="margin">Rom. 6 23. Ezech. 18. v. 4.</note>
                  <hi>The wages of sinne is death. The soule that sinneth, that shall die.</hi> Here is shewed that by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of sinne we take the readie course to loose our soules. And is it not so said of omitting to doe good? yes. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, shall be hewen downe, and cast into the fire,</hi> Mat. 3.10. <hi>The vnprofitable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant</hi> that did no good with his talent, <hi>was cast into vtter darknesse,</hi> Mat 25.30. So then, omission of good, as well as commission of euill, brings to destruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> is readie to illustrate this vnto vs very plainely.
<pb facs="tcp:177089:16"/>We see in <hi>Nature,</hi> there are <hi>two wayes</hi> of killing the body, <hi>one positiue</hi> by offering violence to it, the <hi>other privatiue,</hi> by withholding the meanes of preseruation from it. Though a mā doe not offer violence to his own, or to anothers body, yet, if he withhold from it the meanes of preseruation, it is all one, both are killing wayes, though not both so quicke and readie. So it is with the <hi>soule,</hi> both these wayes it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed. He that offers violence vnto his soule by cōmitting of finne (as by stabbing it with outragious oaths, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fings, by poysoning it with the venemous potions of drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Cups, by gashing it with oppression and crueltie;
<note place="margin">Esa 3.17.</note> by grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of it in grinding the faces of the poore to enlarge his possessions, by wounding it and beating it with the heauie, grieuous, and mortall blowes of pride, presumption, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, fornication, fraud, and vniust dealing, lying and slander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, murder &amp; quarrelling, enuie and malice-bearing &amp;c. He that offers violence to his soule by committing these or the like sinnes) And he, that withholds from his soule the meanes of preseruation (in being negligent in hearing the word of God, and receauing the Sacrament, cold and carelesse in Prayer, slow and slack in the actions of mortification, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine meditations, temperance, sobernesse, fasting, watching,
<note place="margin">As of Ghrists death &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion.</note> fludying, labouring in his vocation, &amp;c. He that thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the meanes of saluation from his soule,) is vnmercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his owne soule, and takes the right way to destroy it. The life of the soule is lost by languishing, as well as by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, by staruing, as well as by stabbing &amp; wounding. As Sinne offers violence to the soule,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mors animae peccatum. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alex. strom l.</hi> 3.</note> is the death and destruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the soule; euery sin being not abandoned, Rom. 6. vlt. especially presumptuous sinnes, Psal. 19.13: so the neglect, and specially the witting, willing, wilfull and totall neglect of the meanes of the soules saluation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omne pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est mors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae Naz. orat.</hi> 36.</note> will be the ruin &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction thereof. So the <hi>Apostle</hi> told the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that <hi>In put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away the word of God, they iudged themselues vnworthie</hi> of euerla sting life, Act. 13.46. Thinke of this, you negatiue men and women, who imagine all is well with you if yee
<pb facs="tcp:177089:17"/>doe no hurt, though you doe no good No, all is not well with you (<hi>donec euacuetur superfluum &amp; subministretur ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nil boni facere hoc ipsum est malum facere.</note> Basil. Asset Cap 55.) Vntill yee abandon vice. And entertaine grace, vntill yee void the corruption of sinne, and receiue the restoratiue, and preseruatiue of Gods word which is able to saue your soules, Act 20.32.</p>
               <p>If a man sicke in his bed, burning of an Ague, fetching his breath with difficultie, looking gastly, speaking idly, should say he were well, thou wouldest not beleeue him: So when thou thy selfe, or when thou seest another man swell with pride, burne with lust, raging with oaths, foming with corrupt, and vncleane communications, railing with slanders, stinking with drunkennesse, rauening with coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse, consuming with enuie, grieued with impatience, plagued with discontent, leprous with ingratitude; if he say he is well, in Christ, and hopes to be saued, beleeue him not: All the world cannot saue him.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17.</note>
                  <hi>If any man be in Christ he is a new creature.</hi> Whom he saueth, them he sanctifieth; Whom he cureth of the sting or guilt of sinne, them he cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of the staine, or corruption of sinne; where he forgiues sinne, there he giues grace to forgoe sinne, where he pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth sinne, there he giues strength to part with it, where he healeth, there he first purgeth with the potion of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Doe not deceiue your selues therefore, thinking all is well, as long as the corrupt, the foule and euill humour of sinne abounds in you vnpurged, vnexpelled. <hi>Purge your hearts yee sinners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4. v. 8.</note>
                  <hi>and purifie your minds yee double minded men. Purge out the old leauen,</hi> 1. Cor. 5.7. Neither thinke that your soules can liue, be well and prosper, vnlesse yee vse duely and daily to feed them, to refresh and cherish them with the food and nourishment thereof, with good dyet. In vaine doth the Potion worke our recoverie, if our euill behauiour afterwards bring a relapse. In vaine shall we purge our hearts by repentance; if after we obserue not the strict dyet of obedience. A good dyet is necessary vnto Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke; obserue it then. Refraine from those corrupt meats
<pb facs="tcp:177089:17"/>whereon your soules haue formerly surfetted, <hi>the leauen of malice, the bread of deceit,</hi> Prov. 20.17.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. v. 7.</note>
                  <hi>the bread of wickednesse.</hi> prov. 4.17. <hi>the bread of idlenesse,</hi> Prov. 31.27. <hi>fullnesse of bread,</hi> Ezech. 16.44. <hi>the drinke-offering of blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 1.6. Prou 4.27. Gal. 5.</note>
                  <hi>the wine of violence, the fruits of the flesh.</hi> all kinde of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit. Let all sinne as an ill dyet be carefully avoided. And be yee mindfull to receaue and feed on the <hi>bread of life, and the water of life,</hi> Christ and his benefits,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6. <hi>Edere est cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi>
                  </note> to receiue and to feed on them by faith, according as they are offered vnto vs in the word, presented in the Sacraments, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving receiued them, be mindfull to digest them by prayer, and holy meditations.</p>
               <p>The body cannot liue, not liue long and strong, without the proper food thereof, as meate, drinke, &amp;c. No more can the soule without the Proper nourishment thereof, as Christ, the Word, Sacrament, and Prayer. The body soone famisheth if it want its food: So will the soule soone pine away, if it want its sustenance and due meales. Be frequent then in hearing the word read, and preached, in receiuing the Sacrament, in Prayer, in holy medirations, in good workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXV. That no man is to neglect the preaching of the Gospell,because God can saue without it.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>word of Grace. Despise not Prophesiing,</hi> 2. Thes. 5. And thus the <hi>light of Nature</hi> likewise teacheth vs. Hee that is endued but with natures dimme light, will not refuse to eate because God can saue him without meate: much lesse wil he that is endued with the <hi>light of Grace,</hi> refuse to heare the word Preached, because God is able to saue without it. If he doe, he tempts the Lord his God. As a man refusing to eate, because God can saue him without meate, tempteth God so doth he, who following his pleasures, and refusing to heare, thinks to be saued.
<note place="margin">Deut. 6. v. 16.</note> Now it is <hi>not safe for</hi> a <hi>man to tempt God</hi> or to put him to this triall, what by his absolute
<pb facs="tcp:177089:18"/>power he can doe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.7.</note> but we are to looke to his actuall power, or what he will doe. And now by his actuall power, we know, and are taught that he will saue by meanes, and no otherwise. <hi>The Naturall life</hi> of the body he will saue by <hi>Naturall meanes,</hi> as meate, drinke, sleepe, &amp;c. and the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all life of the soule, he will saue by <hi>spirituall meanes,</hi> as by the preaching of the Gospell,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> so it is written, <hi>The Gospell is the power of God vnto saluation,</hi> Rom. 1.19. <hi>It pleaseth God by the foolishnesse of preaching</hi> (that is by the meanes of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which some count foolishnesse) <hi>to saue them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</hi> As long then, as God by his actuall power, affords thee the meanes of saluation, doe not neglect them, trusting to his absolute power. Where God affords ordinarie means, there he shewes he will saue no otherwise. When the Children of Israell were in the wildernesse where no means were,
<note place="margin">Exod. 16.15. Ioh. 6.31.</note> God fed them miraculously, <hi>with Manna from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> he gaue them bread from heauen to eate: But when they were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterward when they were brought to <hi>Canaan,</hi> where meanes were, where they might sow and reape, then <hi>Manna Ceased.</hi> God did no longer shew his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute power in feeding them miraculously with <hi>Manna</hi> from heauen, when he gaue them meanes on earth. While thou liuest then in the <hi>Church,</hi> where thou mayest partake of the ordinarie meanes, vse them, if thou wouldest be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished in hope of <hi>eternall life.</hi> Remember that as for Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, so for spirituall life, he must eate, that will liue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXVI. That no man,be he euer so great and eminent for learning, for wisedome, for wealth and honour, is to neglect the hearing of Gods word, and exercising him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe therein.</head>
               <p>Thus <hi>the word of grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudges. 5. v. 3. Psal. 49. v. 1.2.</note>
                  <hi>heare O yee kings, giue eare O yee Princes. Heare yee this O yee Priests,</hi> Hos. 5.10. <hi>Heare yee this all yee people: Ponder it with your eares yee that dwell in
<pb facs="tcp:177089:18"/>the world; high and low rich and poore, one with another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This wisedome the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> is readie to instruct vs in. We see in <hi>Nature,</hi> there is no man be he euer so strong, euer so well in his health, euer so liuely and lusty, euer so learned and wise, euer so rich and honourable, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to eate his meate, to take his due meales, to eat and drinke. Naie the stronger, and the better that a man is in his health, the more duly and freely he will take his food, and the richer, and the more honourable he is, the more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plentifully he will haue it, and take it. And now Christ as he is offered in his word, presented in his sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, receiued by faith, digested by prayer,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6. v. 50.</note> and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the same to the soule, that bread is to the body. Why then should not any, that hath a liuing, a healthie, an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing soule desire to eate of this bread? Why should not the high as well as the low? The rich aswell as the poore? The wise as well as the ignorant and foolish? The noble as well as the ignoble? The Prince as well the peasant, euery one as well as any one, attend vpon the word of God and his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, the food of the soule? Can any, the healthiest, the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiest, the wisest and mightiest, the best of vs all, liue without his due meales? And how should the wisest &amp; most vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing soule liue without his food? Is not the appetite the sharper, and greater the more healthie and strong we are in our bodyes? &amp; verily so it is in the state of the soule. Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer men think of their great knowledge, &amp; learning, as that they need not heare sermons and frequent the Church, as other meaner men doe. Yet this is certaine. The healthier, the stronger, and better any man is in his soule, the more is his appetite to the word of God, and the more he abounds in wisedōe &amp; spirituall vnderstanding the more he abounds in loue and desire to the sincere milke of the word,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 1. Cor. 13.9. 1. Tim. 4.6.</note> that he may grow thereby, knowing that as yet we know but in part, and that part which we doe know, we are apt to forget without a remembrancer, &amp; that which we doe remember, we are slow to performe, without Gods speciall grace and
<pb facs="tcp:177089:19"/>strength, and this strength we must seeke in the hearing of the word,
<note place="margin">Quod iubet iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat.</note> for as it is a meanes to teach vs to know the will of God, so to inable vs to doe it, as bread is a meanes to strengthen a man to doe his worke. In the creation, Gods <hi>fiat,</hi> or commandement, gaue being to the creatures: so it is after a sort in the regeneration, his <hi>fiat,</hi> or saying, <hi>be yee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 15. Mat. 5. vlt.</note>
                  <hi>be yee perfect, be not faithlesse but beleeuing, be sober, be at peace, be doers of the word.</hi> Be so and so; is a meanes to haue it so,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> to effect it so. So then whosoeuer thou art, <hi>despise not prophesying</hi> or preaching, but giue attendance to it, if not to be informed,
<note place="margin">Verbum Dei vivum &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vificans.</note> yet to be reformed, and conformed to the will of God, heare that thou maiest obserue, and doe what is commanded thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXVII. That superiours,and men of great and eminent place, or grace aboue others, are not to despise and contemne their inferiours for their meane and low estate farre beneath them.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Booke of Grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18 v. 10.</note>
                  <hi>See that yee despise not one of these little-ones. Why doest thou despise thy brother,</hi> Rom. 14.10. <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another?</hi> 1. Cor. 4.7. <hi>Be not high minded, but condescend to them of low degree,</hi> Rom. 12.19.</p>
               <p>Learne this also from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> The head though it be advanced aboue the rest of the members, yet it doth not proudly insult vpon them, but it stoopeth and boweth to helpe the meanest and lowest, euen the foote if it be hurt or stand in need. And so againe if the right hand be ready, plyant, and more serviceable then the left, it doth not despise, but beare with it, and help it, &amp; if one legge be stronger then another, we will spare the weaker, &amp; put the stronger to more vse. What doth this teach vs? But that they which haue more gifts, should not despise, but help them that haue fewer. Besides there is no man absolute in this
<pb facs="tcp:177089:19"/>world, nor euer shall be as long as he hath any being here.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>ad omnia quare</hi> 1 Cor. 12.21.</note> The head cannot say to the foote, I haue no need of thee. The master cannot well be without his man. Nor the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord without his tenants, nor yet the King without his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as <hi>Occam</hi> the schooleman told <hi>Lewis</hi> the Emperour.
<note place="margin">Trittenham. in vita Occam.</note>
                  <hi>Defend me with thy sword, and I will defend thee with my pen.</hi> Againe the eye is honoured with that necessary, and noble sense of seeing; and so is the eare with that worthy and needfull sense of hearing, and the nose is preferred before them both in that profitable and vsefull sense of smelling: Thus he that taketh place before all in some things, must be content to giue place, and to come behind others in some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else. Let this teach thee to contemne none that are inferiours to thy selfe in grace, in place, in estate, &amp; meanes, in any gift. Remember that he that withholds his clemencie, because the subject is base, denies a remedie to his wounded foote, because it is an infenour part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="doctrine">
               <head>That inferiours ought not to envy at their superiours, because of their greatnesse aboue them, but to be content with their place.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord, <hi>frett not thy selfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 37. v. 1.7.</note>
                  <hi>neither be thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, grieue not at him whose way doth prosper. Lay aside all malice, and envies, and evill speakings,</hi> 1. Pet. 2.1. <hi>Let your conversation be without covetousnesse, and be content with such things as yee haue,</hi> Heb. 13.5. <hi>I haue learned in whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever state I am therewith to bee content</hi> saith S. Paul <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>And this we may learne likewise, and that from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> The foot doth not envy the head, because it is preferred before it, as more honourable; neither is it discontented, because it is clad in leather, when it may bee there is a chaine of Gold about the necke, or a pretious stone about the finger. No more should we envy any that be in higher place for the credit, honour, and respect which
<pb facs="tcp:177089:20"/>they haue aboue vs. It is a foule fault when we cannot haue the credit that others haue, to envie them for it: What if thou hast not so strong a faith as <hi>Abraham?</hi> Or such a gift of prayer as <hi>Dauid?</hi> hast thou any measure of saving faith? or any gift of prayer at all? If thou hast any measure of sauing faith, any gift of true prayer thou art well. He that had but <hi>two talents,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> was as much commended and went into his <hi>Masters ioy,</hi> as well as he that had fiue. It is a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to be any member of the body of Christ. Though thou beest not an eye but a foot, thou art quickned by the soule, as well as the eye, &amp; thou shalt be saued as well as the eye. The soule seeth by the eyes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>August. Hom.</hi> 186. <hi>De Temp. prope finem.</hi>
                  </note> walketh by the feete, <hi>vitam dat omnibus, officia singulis,</hi> giueth life to all, but executeth diverse functions by diverse members, though the foot sees not, yet it liues as well as the eye. <hi>Officia diversa, vita com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis</hi> saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Augustine.</hi> The offices are diverse but the life is common. <hi>Sic est in Ecclesia Dei, singulipropria operantur, pariter vivunt:</hi> so it is among the elect in the Church, the spirit of God fitteth this man for this imployment, that for that, but sanctifieth them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXIX That wee ought to haue a Sympathy or a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeling of one anothers misery and to be ready to helpe and comfort one another.</head>
               <p>Thus the word of Grace.
<note place="margin">Heb. 13. v. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which suffer adversity, as being your selues in the body. Put on as the elect of God, bowels of mercy and compassion</hi> Colos. 3.12. <hi>Mourne with them that mourne,</hi> Rom. 12.5. <hi>Bee kindly affectioned one to another.</hi> v. 10.</p>
               <p>This wee may learne from the <hi>Booke of nature.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. v. 26.</note>
                  <hi>If one member suffer, all the members suffer with it.</hi> If the foot bee hurt, the rest of the members will condole with it, and not only so, but joyne together to helpe, and to heale it, the head will stoope, the mouth will speake, the eye will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb facs="tcp:177089:20"/>and looke, the backe will bend, the hand will stretch, and put forth it selfe to helpe what it may; all will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to doe their best for the meanest member, that which is more feeble, lesse honourable, yea for the vncomely part, for every part that lacketh. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.22.23.24. Now if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong these members, which all except the head, <hi>are brute and vnreasonable,</hi> there is such a Sympathy and Harmony, much more ought there to be amongst vs Christians, who are governed not only by reason, but by the spirit of God. Our sympathy and fellow-feeling of one anothers misery and distresse, should be more quicke and liuely, in as much as we haue a double life in vs, even the <hi>life of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>life of Grace:</hi> for the more life, the greater sense, the more quicke in hearing, seeing, smelling, tasting, touching. And verily hee that is not touched with a fellow-feeling of his brothers, and others miseries, may suspect worthily, that he is not a liuely member of Christ:
<note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 16.</note>
                  <hi>for Christs body is knit and coupled together throughout every ioynt, whereby one ministreth to another.</hi> If then wee doe not beare ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burthen, and feele one anothers misery, wee are not knit together by the sinews of loue, and if not to the body, no part of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXX That wee should endeavour with all diligence to hold vnity and concord one with another.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Endeavour to keepe the vnity of the spirit in the bond of peace: if it be possible, as much as lyeth in you, liue peaceably with all men,</hi> Rom. 12.18. <hi>Aboue all things haue fervent loue among your selues.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.8.</p>
               <p>This wee are taught likewise by the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> In the body, the members, though diverse and of diverse of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, yet sweetly agree and hold together, mutually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their duties one to another, without jarring or contending. The head though it be lifted vp aboue the rest of the members, yet he scornes not the feete, as to say, I
<pb facs="tcp:177089:21"/>haue no need of you, no more doth the eye say to the hand I haue no need of you. Here is no disdaining, no discord or falling out, but every fellow-member is helpefull &amp; louing to his fellow-members, and willing to yeeld to every one that which belongs to them. Yea sometimes more then it deserues, as in walking, if one foot hit the other, so as to hurt it, or to make it ake, the foot hurt or grieved, doth not hit the other againe, and returne blow for blow, but is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and holds good accord with the other for all that. By this course of nature let vs learne to hold vnity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord one with another, and not to returne evill for evill, but <hi>to overcome evill with good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12. vlt.</note> The incolumity of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy depends vpon the concord of the parts, in the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all performance of their duties: so the well-fare of the Church, when wee shew our selues to bee members one of another. As the sinews in the body, so is loue in the Church or common-wealth,
<note place="margin">Colos. 3.14.</note> even <hi>the very bond of perfectnesse.</hi> If a sinew be broken, it is a hazarding of the body, a hindrance to a mans welfare, till it be knit againe. Now the breach of loue, is as the breach of a sinew, yea of many sinews. We can never be well, if this sinew be broken, till it be knit vp againe.
<note place="margin">Colos. 2.2.</note>
                  <hi>Be yee therefore knit together in loue. I beseech you brethren, by the name of our Lord Iesus Christ, that yee all speake the same thing, and that there bee no division among you, but that yee bee perfectly ioyned together in the same minde, and in the same iudgement.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. The spirit of man doth not quicken any member or part separated from the body:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>August, Ser.</hi> 1. <hi>Adfratres in Eterno.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>The dry bones which Ezechiel saw scattered in the field, had no life in them, till they were gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bone to his bone</hi> Ezech. 37.7. So the spirit of God doth not animate, and comfort these who cut off and divide themselues from Christs mysticall body.
<note place="margin">Psal 133.</note>
                  <hi>Behold then how good and ioyfull a thing it is, for brethren to dwell together in vnity, behold and labour to hold it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:21"/>
               <head>XXXI That to revenge our selues,especially in every petty miury of words or deeds, is a signe of great weaknesse and corruption, not of a good spirit, or mettall.</head>
               <p>Thus the Word of Grace.
<note place="margin">Prou. 16. v. 32.</note>
                  <hi>Hee that is slow to anger is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the mighty, and hee that ruleth his spirit then hee that conquereth a Citty. He that deferreth his anger, is a man of discretion, and he that passeth by an offence, it is a grace to him</hi> Prov. 19.11. but not so to him that revengeth. <hi>Desire of revenge resteth in the bosome of a foole</hi> saith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 7. v. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> is ready to teach vs. In Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we see, it is a signe of a weake stomacke, not to be able to beare and concoct lighter meats: So it is an argument of a weake minde, not to digest small wrongs, as the giuing the lye, (a naughty word I confesse) but yet our firmity in grace should be more, then to be moued to revenge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. When a man cannot endure to be touched, it is a signe that he is not sound: So when wee cannot endure a crosse word, without thinking of revenge, it is a plaine symptome of an vnsound and corrupt minde. I say then in the words of the Apostle. <hi>Dearely beloved, avenge not your selues, but rather giue place vnto wrath,</hi> Rom. 12.9. <hi>Say not I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence evill,</hi> Prov. 20.22. <hi>Say not I will doe to him as hee hath done to mee.</hi> Prov. 24 29. The words of revenge are forbidden, much more the works.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXII That wee should avoide all busy-medling with things not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to vs, and beyond the bounds of our calling.</head>
               <p>Thus the Booke of Grace.
<note place="margin">1. Thes. 4. v. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Study to be quiet medling with your owne businesse. Let every man abide in the calling wherein he is placed.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.24.</p>
               <p>This wee are taught by the <hi>light of Nature.</hi> In <hi>Nature</hi> we see the eye meddles not with hearing, nor the eare
<pb facs="tcp:177089:22"/>with seeing, nor the foot with either of them both, but each member keepes his owne office, and that it lookes to: By this wee may learne not to arrogate to our selues any thing, out of our owne calling, but to containe our selues within our owne bounds and limits. If a mote should fall into the eye, were the foot a fit member to bee thrust into the eye, to plucke it out? Not so. For though the foot bee sensible of the paine, yet it leaues the helping of it to the hand, whose office it is. Thus it should bee in the Church and Common-wealth. Every one should meddle with his owne office, and keepe himselfe to his owne calling. There are many who chuse &amp; delight rather to be seene skilfull in other mens offices, then to employ themselues in their own. This is a foule fault. If the feete should grow where the hands are, it would make the body monstrous: So when men will not containe themselues within their order, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and calling, it is to make the Church a Babylon, a very confusion. It is neither fit nor comely, for the people to meddle with the office of Magistrates, directing them how they should governe, nor with the calling of Ministers, teaching them how to preach. If things be amisse, let pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men pray for a reformation; but leaue it to them whose calling it is to reforme. Let the foot leaue the dressing of the body to the hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXIII. That wee should seeke the common good and not our owne private alone.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord.
<note place="margin">Gal. 6. v. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Doe good vnto all men. Let no man seeke his owne but every man anothers wealth,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> will teach vs thus much, if wee doe obserue it. We see, no member is for it selfe alone, but for the good of the whole, and the vse one of another. The eye doth direct the head, and the hand guard the eye, the nose smells for all; the tongue speakes for all, and the hand workes for all. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part seekes anothers, and not his owne good alone. So
<pb facs="tcp:177089:22"/>should wee imploy our gifts and talents, not only to our owne particular good, but to the benefit of other, even to the generall good of the whole Church. As the stomacke receiues the meat and drinke at our hands, not for it selfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but to concoct it, and prepare it, to the benefit of the rest of the body: So we receiue gifts at Gods hands; but not for our owne particular vse altogether, but to the end that wee should impart,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> and <hi>distribute thereof to the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of the Saints;</hi> of the poore members of Christ. I say then in the words of the Apostle, <hi>As every man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the gift, even so Minister the same one to anothe, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God,</hi> 1 Pet 4 10. The Lord hath not only giuen a man a mind, by which he may haue intelligence with his maker. But also therewithall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and instruments of the body, by which he may haue intelligence with men, and communicate the good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his mind vnto others. And this is to intimate vnto vs: That the Lord hath made no man for himselfe, that hee should locke vp, and keepe within himselfe all the good that God hath communicated to him: but as first hee made him for his owne glory, so secondarily for the vse and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of other men. If man had beene created for God only, he should not haue needed a tongue, for the Lord knowes the meaning of the mind without the tongue. And if he had beene made for himselfe only, the motions of the mind had beene sufficient for himselfe also. But God hath made one man to be a comfort to another, and therefore hath given him such Organs as whereby every man may giue intelligence of his mind to another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXIV That wee should honour and obey the higher powers,the Magistrates and Ministers.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>
                  <hi>Let every soule be subiect vnto the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the higher powers. Subiect your selues to every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man for the Lords sake, whether it bee vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:177089:23"/>King as supreame, or vnto Governours, as vnto them that are sent by him, for the punishment of evill doers, and for the praise of them that doe well</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.14. <hi>Obey your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and submit your selues vnto them, for they watch as being to giue account for your soules,</hi> Heb. 13.17.</p>
               <p>This wee may learne from the booke of Nature. All the members of the body obey &amp; follow the direction of the Head &amp; Heart. So should we follow the direction of those that be placed over vs. It is a maimed body that wants ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two hands Now Moses and Aaron, that is, the Civill and Ecclesiasticall Magistrate, are as it were Gods two hands, to rule and governe his people, according to that of the Kingly Prophet David,
<note place="margin">Psal. 77, vlt.</note>
                  <hi>Thou leddest thy people like sheepe by the hands of Moses and Aaron.</hi> God himselfe is the generall and principall leader, <hi>(for the whole world is his)</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are Gods hands, his Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to rule here in earth, the one with the word, the other by the sword. <hi>Touch not the Lords annointed, and doe his Prophets no harme.</hi> Let <hi>Moses</hi> the Prince, and <hi>Aaron</hi> the Priest be had in honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXV That wee should be willing to be at charge and to take painet for the maintenance of the King and state.</head>
               <p>Thus the Booke of Grace.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.6.7.</note>
                  <hi>Pay you tribute, render to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his due, tribute to whom tribute is due. Render to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar the things that are Caesars,</hi> Mat. 22.18. <hi>Our Saviour Christ</hi> (though himselfe free) <hi>yet paied tribute vnto Caesar,</hi> yea and rather then he would not pay it, and so giue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of offence to the Ruler, <hi>He wrought a miracle to pay it,</hi> Mat. 17.25.26.27. <hi>This is written for our Learning</hi> 1 Cor. 10.</p>
               <p>And thus we may learne likewise from the <hi>Booke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> In the naturall body, the inferiour members, as the hands and feete are content and willing to labour and to take paines for the head and stomacke, though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure
<pb facs="tcp:177089:23"/>&amp; spend a great part of what they get: so should wee be content and willing to doe service, and to take paines for the King and state, which are as the Head and Stomacke of the body Politike, the Common wealth. There is a notable story in <hi>Livie</hi> which fitly serueth to this purpose, and the story is this. There were very often greevous broiles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Commons &amp; Nobles of <hi>Rome:</hi> once amongst the rest, when the People had banded themselues, and that the Common-wealth was in danger, the Senate sent vnto the people one <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> a famous Oratour, to perswade them to quietnesse, and obedience, and being come, he tells them this Parable. On a time (saith hee) the members of the body fell out with the stomacke, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected against it, that it devoured all, and idly and sluggish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lay in the middest of the body, whilest the rest of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy laboured fullsore, wherevpon the foot refused to stirre and carry the stomacke, the hand refused to put meat into the mouth, the mouth to receiue it, and the teeth to chew it. Now what followed? The stomacke being empty, the eye beganne to be dimme, the hand weake, the feet feeble, all the members began to faint, and the whole body to wither; so at last, they were content, yea of necessity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to grow friends with the stomacke. And they lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the stomacke is most profitable to all the members of the body. And by this parable he quieted the people, and brought them to concord with the state againe. And so by this I would haue you learne not to mutter, or to think it much what ye doe for the King and state, for what they receiue at your hands, they imploy it to the generall good of the whole kingdome, they returne it like the stomacke to the good of the members of the body politike.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:24"/>
               <head>XXXVI That the life and wellfare of our supreame head, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,the King, is to be tendered and preferred before our owne, or any other mans.</head>
               <p>Thus the Booke of Grace. <hi>I exhort that supplications and prayers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. v. 1.2.</note>
                  <hi>and intercessions, and giuing of thanks bee made for all men</hi> but namely and primarily for <hi>Kings.</hi> The people of Israell did preferre the life and safety of their Soveraigne King <hi>Dauid</hi> before <hi>ten thousand of their owne liues,</hi> 2. Sam. 18.3. this our duty likewise.</p>
               <p>And this wee may learne from the course of <hi>Nature.</hi> All the members haue care one of another, but especially of the head and heart. If the head doe ake, all the humors of the armes runne to the head, and therefore the armes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come small and slender because they want their proper nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And so if the heart be sicke, or in dangers or feare, the outward heat retires inward to comfort the heart, so that the body lookes outwardly pale. Yea if the head or heart be in danger, <hi>(periculis se exponunt)</hi> the other members will hazard limme and life to defend and saue them: So should wee doe for our head the <hi>King,</hi> or our heart the <hi>Queene:</hi> wee ought to haue speciall care of them. Wee are to care one for another, to pray one for another and to doe good one for another, but specially for Kings and them that are in authority, wee are to preferre their liues before ten thousands of ours, as the people of Israell did. If a member, or some of the inferiour members be cut off, yet the body may liue and doe indifferently well, but if the head be cut off, there is no hope of life, it can neveuer doe well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXVII That they should behaue themselues well,both in word and deed, that be superiours.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord vnto <hi>Ioshua</hi> Captaine of the hoste of Israell,
<note place="margin">Ioshua. 1. v. 7.</note>
                  <hi>Be thou strong and very couragious that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est obserue to doe according to all the law which Moses my
<pb facs="tcp:177089:24"/>servant commanded thee, turne not from it to the right hand or to the left.</hi> So againe to King <hi>Salomon,</hi> And thou <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, serue the Lord with a perfect heart and a willing minde,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. So likewise to <hi>Timothy, Be thou an exsample of the beleeuers in word, in conversation,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.12.</p>
               <p>This we are taught by the light of nature. If the head be well all the body is the better for it.
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>
                  <hi>If the eye be single the whole body is full of light.</hi> But if the head aketh, or is ill at ease, all the body is the worse for it: So it is in the Church, or Common-wealth, or family. If the Magistrates, the Ministers, the Parents, the Maisters, if these, (which be as the heads) doe well and be sound in the faith, right in the vnderstanding, renewed in the will, quicke in the senses, of hearing, seeing, smelling, tasting &amp; touching that which is good; Then all is the better for it, the whole body is the more liuely and ready to good: But if these doe amisse, it cannot be well with the members, the inferiours; if the head be deafe, and blinde, and dumbe, and giddy or sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish, how shall the other members heare, and see, and speake, and behaue themselues well? they cannot. Woe is the body, where the head is phrenzie, drunken, idle or the like. See thou be not so, who art placed as head aboue others: but as the head doth heare and see and tast, and smell for the good of the inferiour members: So doe thou in that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God hath set thee, see that thy eye bee not evill,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6. v. 23.</note> but single, and then thy body shall not bee darke, but light. A good Magistrate, or Minister, or Maister over a perverse people, is a sound head over a surfetted body: and a good Commonalty or society or family and a bad ruler, is a healthfull body and a head akeing, either are occasions of ruine, both sound preservatiues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXVIII That Gouernours and Commanders should regard Souldiert, and allow them maintenance.</head>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Booke of Grace. Be content with your wages,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 3.14.</note>
                  <hi>the
<pb facs="tcp:177089:25"/>the labourer is worthy of his reward,</hi> 1. Tim. 5.18. <hi>the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is worthy of his meate,</hi> Mat. 10.10. <hi>Thou shalt giue him his hire (saith the Lord) neither shall the Sunne goe downe vpon it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 24. v. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This lesson also Nature teacheth vs. In Nature and the Naturall Constitution of the body, the hands are as soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to execute the resolution of the heart. And the heart from her virtuall Conduits, sendeth bloud to warme the hands: Such affinity, and alliance ought to be betweene the Gouernour that ruleth, &amp; the souldier that executeth; There must some sweet showers of Gold Come out of his Coffers to refresh them, or they waxe dull, and are deuoured with idlenesse, so that when they should defend the heart, their fingers are numbde, as that they cannot fight, because they want the vse of feeling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="doctrine">
               <head>XXXIX That iustice iustly executed,is the life and welfare of the Common-wealth.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord,
<note place="margin">Esa. 5.6.1.</note>
                  <hi>keepe yee iudgment and doe iustice. Doe this, that it may goe well with you, that yee may proffier,</hi> Iosh. 1. <hi>The King that faithfully iudgeth the poore, his throne shall be established for euer,</hi> Prov. 29.14. Iosiah <hi>did doe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iustice, and then it was well with him,</hi> ler. 22.15.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> will teach vs to acknowledge this. For as we know the Constitution of a mans body by his pulse. If it stirre not at all, then we know he is dead, if it stirre violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then we take him to be in a feauer, if it keepe an equall stroke, then we know he is sound and whole: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we may Iudge of the state of the Cōmon-wealth, by the manner of the execution of Iustice therein. For Iustice is the pulse of the Common-wealth. If Iustice be violent, then the Cōmon-wealth is in a feauer, in a bad estate; if it stirre not at all, then the Common-wealth is dead. But if it haue an equal stroke, the Iust and ordinarie course, then the Cōmon-wealth is in a good constitution, it is sound and whole, And So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:25"/>
               <head>That there is but one Church.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Lord</hi> speaking of his Church, <hi>My doue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant 6.9. Ioh. 10.16.</note>
                  <hi>my vndefiled is but one, the only one of her Mother. One fold.</hi> True it is, this one Church may haue, and hath many parts: as some part in <hi>England,</hi> some in <hi>Scotland,</hi> some in <hi>France,</hi> and some in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and some in all parts of the world, and yet all these parts make but one Militant Church here on earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> will plainely illustrate this, for <hi>as the body is one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. v. 12.</note>
                  <hi>and hath many members, and all the members of that one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being many, are one body: Even so is the Church of Christ: Wee being many are one body in Christ, and every one, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers members,</hi> Rom. 12.45. <hi>There is neither Iew nor Greeke, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female, but wee are all one in Christ Iesus, Gal.</hi> 3.28. One, not as tyed to any one place, as to Rome; or to any one person, as to the Pope, as the Romanists would haue it. But one, as living by one and the same spirit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Haruaeus de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testate papae. C.</hi> 23.</note> and ruled by one and the same Lord; and professing one and the same faith; having one and the same hope, and having beene Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with one and the same Baptisme. The Church is one in this respect, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> in his Epistle to the Ephesians plainely declareth, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.4.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLI That Christ is the supreame head of the Church,and not the Pope.</head>
               <p>Thus the word of Truth. <hi>God raised him from the dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 1. v. 20. ad finem. c. 4. Cap. 5.23.</note>
                  <hi>and set him at his owne right hand in the heavenly places; Farre aboue all principalities and powers, and might and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and every name that is named, not only in this world but also in the world to come. And hath put all things vnder his feete, and gaue him to be the head over all things to the Church; which is his body, the fulnesse of him that filleth all
<pb facs="tcp:177089:26"/>in all. The head of every man is Christ. He is the head of the body the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.3.</note> Colos. 1.18. <hi>The head of all Principality and Power,</hi> Colos. 8.10. <hi>There bee others that are called heads.</hi> As <hi>The Prince is called the head of his people because of his Soveraignety and Power over them,</hi> Exod. 6.14. &amp; 18.25. And <hi>the husband is called the head of his wife,</hi> because he is the more worthy sexe, and her Lord and Ruler, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. And the Pastor and pincipall member in any society is called the head. <hi>The honourable man is the Head,</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>Esa.</hi> 9.15. but these are either po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall, or oeconomicall, not spirituall heads: particular not vniversall heads. Kings &amp; Princes are Chiefe and supreame heads vnder Christ of Certaine particular Kingdomes, and Dominions committed vnto them. As our Gratious King <hi>Charles</hi> is the Chiefe &amp; Supreame Head of this Kingdome and other his Dominions. But not of the whole militant Church here on earth.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Booke of Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels Art.</hi> 37.</note> This he doth not take vpon him to be, As the Pope doth: but to be the head of his people, to haue chiefe power in this Realme of England, and other his Dominions. As for the Catholike or vniversall Church, dispersed over the face of the whole Earth, we acknowledge not any particular man to bee the head thereof, but the man Christ Iesus.
<note place="margin">Ephes. 5.23.</note>
                  <hi>He is given by the Father to be the head over all things to the Church, which is his body.</hi> And him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone wee acknowledge for such, for the vniversall King; the vniversall Bishop. There is no man that can doe the office of a head to the whole body of the Church, but hee, in looking out, and caring for the safety and well fare of it. Other men may see to the ordering of some particular member thereof. As the Bishop of Rome may see to his Diocesse; &amp; other Bishops to theirs. But to see to the whole body of the vniversall Church, that is more then any meere man can doe. Some in a pride may take it vpon them, as the Bishops of Rome doe, but performe it they cannot. Christ is the only Head that can doe this, whose eyes are in every place,
<note place="margin">Prou. 17.</note> beholding the evill and the good. And there
<pb facs="tcp:177089:26"/>is none else besides him, that can doe it.</p>
               <p>This the Booke of <hi>Nature</hi> will goe neere to teach vs. It is not vsuall for one body to haue more heads then one, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be a monster: Now the Church is one body,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.12. Psal. 45. Cant. 1.15.16. C. 2.10.13.</note> and it is no monstrous body, but a faire and comely body, a <hi>body fitly ioyned together, Ephes.</hi> 4.16 And can such a body haue more then one head? Must it needs haue a double head? An Imperiall &amp; a Ministeriall, as the Romists say? Why, if Christ had assigned the Pope to be his Ministeriall head, then his body the Church should scarce bee so faire and comely as he saith of it, hauing at so netime no head, as at the death and vacancy of Popes. Sometimes three heads at once as in a schisme. Sometimes monsters for her head, as Magicians, Villaines. But Christ hath assigned no such heads for his Church. Hee is and will be the Head of his Church him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, he is not absent that he should need a deputy to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his place, but is alwaies present with his Church, by his word and spirit. So himselfe saith, <hi>Loe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 28. vlt.</note>
                  <hi>I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to the end of the World.</hi> And againe, <hi>where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them.</hi> Mat. 18. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLII That the Romane Church is not the Catholike Church.</head>
               <p>Catholike is a Greeke word,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>i. e. de toto vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, vel quia per totum est. Aug. de vnitate Eccles. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Athanas. quest.</hi> 71.</note> and in English it is as much as Vniversall, or generall, that is the signification of the word Catholike. Now the Church of Rome howsoever she takes vpon her the name of Catholike, or vniversall Church; yet the truth is, she is not so, for S. <hi>Paul</hi> writ vnto the Church of God at Corinth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. Vnto the Church of <hi>Galatia, Gal.</hi> 1.2. Vnto the Church of the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.1. and to diverse others as well as to the Church of Rome <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. So that the Church of Rome cannot rightly be said to be the Catholike or Vniversall Church, Others being the Church of God as well as Shee. The Church of Rome, at the best, is but a part or particular,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:27"/>member of the Catholike, or vniverfall Church of Christ? And a particular Church cannot be said to be the vniversall, Vnlesse a finger can be an hand, or an hand the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or a part become the whole. And now the very light of Nature will teach vs that this cannot be. A finger cannot be an hand, or an hand the whole dody, or a part become the whole. And no more can the Romane Church being a part, be well said to be the Catholike, or the whole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLIII That wee ought to approue of theimparity of callings, and of the vnequall division of Gods gifts in the Church.</head>
               <p>Thus it is witten,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note>
                  <hi>God dealeth to every man a measure of faith,</hi> a portion of his gifts, not all gifts to one, nor the same gifts to every one, in the same measure, but <hi>every man hath his proper gift of God, one after this manner, another after that,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 15.15.</note> 1 Cor. 7.7. c. 12.11. To one he giueth <hi>fiue Talents,</hi> to another <hi>two,</hi> to another <hi>one talent.</hi> There are diversity of gifts, Different callings &amp; rankes of men assigned by Christ in his Church. <hi>When he ascended vp on high he gaue some A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, some Prophets, some Evangelists, and some Pastors, &amp; Teachers,</hi> Ephes 4.11. These were not all of equall ranke. The Apostles were in dignity aboue the Evangelists, and the 70 Disciples;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza in Act. Apost.</hi> 1.2.</note> and for authority both in and over the Church, as twelue. Patriarches saith <hi>Beza.</hi> We may not then condemne all superiority among men, saying that every man should be equall for calling, and that there should be no difference of persons among Christians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sleidan. Com. lib</hi> 5. <hi>Admon. to the par.</hi>
                  </note> as the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, and Disciplinarians would haue it.</p>
               <p>If we looke into the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> wee may learne better wisdome then this. The <hi>Body</hi> of man, in regard of the admirable composition thereof, of many and different mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is the more beautifull and comely: And so is the <hi>Church</hi> also much more beautifull, in that it consists of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers sorts of men, of different degrees, and diversity of gifts
<pb facs="tcp:177089:27"/>and graces. If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? If all the members were alike, all head, or all eye, or all eare, what beautie, what comelinesse were in the body? Surely none at all. Beauty consists in the variety of colours, and in a concinne disposition of different parts. And so the variety which is in the diverse sorts of men, in the Church, in the divers degrees of offices, in the divers measure of gifts, wonderfully sets forth the beauty of the Church. He then that affects in the Church an hotch-potch parity, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Marres the Church which is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a body fitly ioyned together by every ioint.
<note place="margin">Eph. 4. v. 16.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLIV. That the Church of Rome is not to be the better thought of for her outward pompe and glory:Nor the Church of England, and the rest of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, the worst to bee thought of for their plaine and meane estate.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.24.</note>
                  <hi>Iudge not according to the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but iudge righteous iudgement.</hi> It is said of Christ, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his conversation here below, that hee had <hi>no forme nor comelinesse, no beauty that we should desire him,</hi> Esa, 53.2. And now it is possible that the body should not be made conformable to the head? Verily the true Church is <hi>predestinated to be conformed to the image of Christ,</hi> Rom. 8.29 To be made of no reputation in the world as hee was made, Phil. 2.7. To become poore, as he did, 2. Cor. 8.9. To suffer as he did suffer, Rom. 8.17. To suffer and to bee perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted euen to death, and that by the princes of the world, the Magistrates, the very same which pretend the title of the Church, the authoritie, succession, and chaire of <hi>Moses,</hi> as he was, 1. Cor. 2.8. whom God did fore-knowe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> he also did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinate to be thus conformed to the image of his Sonne. Iudge not then the better of that church that hath outward
<pb facs="tcp:177089:28"/>glory and lustre, nor the worst of that which wants it, if she be <hi>all glorious within.</hi> Psal. 45.14.</p>
               <p>Heare what Nature saith to this. A painted face may seeme more beautifull then a naturall; Counterfeit Gold may haue a gayer shew then good; And a faigned friend may be more ceremonious in complements then a true one; A strumpet may haue statelier and gayer apparell then an honest woman: So it is in the visible Church. Hypocrites may goe as farre in outward worship, as the best beleeuers: as <hi>Cain</hi> in sacrificing,
<note place="margin">Luc. 18.11.12.13.</note>
                  <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> in outward penance, the <hi>Pharisee</hi> in outward forme of praying; yea hee can bee more large, and eloquent then the <hi>Publican.</hi> As <hi>Christ</hi> then said of himselfe, the head, so I say of the Church, his mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body,
<note place="margin">Luc 7.23.</note>
                  <hi>Blessed is hee that is not offended in her,</hi> for her meane estate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLV. That the Church of England is not to be forsaken,or sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from, by reason of some supposed errours and corruptions therein.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10. v. 25.</note>
                  <hi>Forsake not the assembling of your selues together, as the manner of some is, but exhort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so much the more, as you see the day approaching.</hi> Christ and his Apostles did not depart from the Churches, though there were amongst them many abuses, &amp; the most of them greater then amongst vs, who haue the word pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached; and the Sacraments rightly administred. To make it appeare, In <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> in our Saviour Christs time, the Eleuē <hi>Tribes</hi> were become <hi>Apostates,</hi> Mar. 23.37. There were in it Scribes, Pharisees, Hypocrites, yea at that time, the doctrine of the Law was corrupted by the false Glosses of the Pharises,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.21. Ioh. 2.14.</note> and the Church it selfe was almost become a denne of theeues, full of buyers, and sellers. And yet Christ did not forsake it, and bodily depart from it, as long as he liued in the forme of a seruant. So againe in the Church of Corinth,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.19.</note> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time, there were some in
<pb facs="tcp:177089:28"/>an heresie; others in incest,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.1.</note> and other some that had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their filthinesse, and many other infirmities, as you may see, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20.21. And yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did not locally separate from them for all this. Not yet from the <hi>Galathians,</hi> though they were <hi>perverted to another doctrine;</hi> embracing a fundamentall error of iustification by workes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2. No more should any man make a separation from our Church of England, by reason of some blemishes and corruptions therein.</p>
               <p>If we looke into the <hi>Book of Nature,</hi> we may learne bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wisdome then so. If the head doe ake, the foot doth not refuse to beare it; or if the eye be blemished, the rest of the members doe not disdaine or contemne it, or whilest it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the body, refuse to haue fellowship with it. No more should any man make separation from the Church, by reason of some infirmities, and corruptions. All diseases and corruptions in man, doe not make a man to be no man, and so to be avoided: but a corrupt man and so to bee pittied: And so all errours and corruptions in a Church, doe not make a Church to be no Church, and so to be forsaken; but a corrupt Church, and so to be prayed for and redressed. To knowe which are annihilating and destroying errours, such as deserue separation. We must vnderstand that <hi>Errours,</hi> &amp; corruptions in a Church, are of <hi>two sorts:</hi> Either such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne <hi>doctrine,</hi> or such as concerne <hi>manners.</hi> Corruption in manners make not no Church but a bad Church. Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in doctrine, are either such as are <hi>citra fundamentum,</hi> besides the foundation; and these trouble: or <hi>circa funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> about the foundation, and these shake: or <hi>contra fundamentum,</hi> against the foundation, and these overturne all. The two former are <hi>weakning Errours,</hi> and doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barte them from being the true Church of God, being but the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12.</note>
                  <hi>building of hay &amp; stubble</hi> on the foundation; the stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burnt (I meane not in the fire of Purgatory) their soules may be saued. The latter are <hi>destroying Errours,</hi> and in these consideration must bee had, whether a Church erreth of
<pb facs="tcp:177089:29"/>weaknesse, or of malice: if it be of weaknesse, then are wee not peremptorily to conclude against such a Church: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> as a church of God, though they were <hi>remoued from him that called them into grace of Christ, vnto another Gospell</hi> or doctrine, holding a <hi>fundamentall errour</hi> of iustification by workes, Gal. 1.2.6, But if it be of malice,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. v. 8.</note> or affected ignorance, like <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> that withstood <hi>Moses, resisting the truth,</hi> then doth such a church cease to be a church, neither is it any longer to be reputed as a church.</p>
               <p>Now our church doth not hold any fundamentall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, the
<note n="*" place="margin">See a little book set forth by the Separatists of the confession of their faith.</note> Separatists themselues being witnesse, or if it doe, not of malice, and affected ignorance not wilfully and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinatly (I dare say) whereby she should bee forsaken. The doctrine of our church is sound, and vncorrupt; being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant to the word of God, as appeares by the Catholike doctrine of the church of England, set forth in the Booke of Articles, with the confirmation thereof out of Scripture.</p>
               <p>But for manners and conversation, though we may iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our selues in respect of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.8.</note> yet herein, <hi>if we say that we haue no sinne, we deceaue our selues, and there is no truth in vs.</hi> What body is there so sound, but hath some excrements? What Church euer breathed in so pure an aire, as that it might not iustly complaine of some thick and vnwholsome evaporations of errour and sinne? But because our Church wants some beauty, hath shee lost her face?
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.5.</note> Because she is blacke, hath shee no comelinesse at all? Because she hath some corruptions, is shee therefore a false Church? corruptions doe not make a false man, but a corrupt man. Let Separatists make the worst they can of our Church, they can make it but a corrupt church, not a false Church. We haue the true word of God preached, the true Sacraments of Christ Iesus administred, which all
<note n="*" place="margin">Bucer. Martyr. Fagius. Calvin. Beza. Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Zanchius. Iunius. Rollocke &amp;c.</note> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in all the reformed churches in Christendome, which now are or haue beene, doe hold to be the infallible tokens of a true church, and are reciprocally converted with the
<pb facs="tcp:177089:29"/>true church. We maintaine every point of the most ancient Creed, wee overthrow not the foundation by any conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. And as yet we haue not receaued a bill of divorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so that they which separate from vs, offer a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie to their mother in flying from her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLVI That the voice of God sounding in his written word,the holy Scripture is the speaking decider of all controversies in the church.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord, <hi>yee erre, not knowing the Scriptures.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12. Ioh 5.39.</note>
                  <hi>Search the Scriptures, they are they that testifie of me. To the Law and to the testimonie, if any speake not according to this word, it is because there is no light in them,</hi> Esa, 8.20. Our Saviour Christ himselfe in his controversie with the Divell, decided the question by Scripture, and gaue the true meaning of one scripture by another, Mat. 4.7. And this hee hath left to be our soueraigne Iudge,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. v. 16</note> our Resoluer and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structer in all doubts. <hi>I haue giuen them thy word,</hi> saith Christ, Ioh. 17.14. <hi>They haue Moses and the Prophets, let them heare them,</hi> Luk. 16.29.</p>
               <p>I, but the Scriptures are dumbe, and cannot speake,
<note place="margin">Ob.</note> (say the Romanists) And how then can they determine contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies, and resolue doubts, being not able to speake? Not able to speake? Why? the Apostle saith,
<note place="margin">Sol. Rom. 9.17.27.</note>
                  <hi>That the Law speaketh,</hi> Rom. 3.19. <hi>That the Scripture saith, yea &amp; cryeth. Esay cryeth concerning Israel, saith the Apostle,</hi> Rom. 9.</p>
               <p>But say that God doth not now speake vnto his people, <hi>by word of mouth,</hi> by a liuly voice, as hee did here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. Cannot he as well resolue them otherwise As <hi>by letter, by a written word?</hi> May not a man speeake, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his minde to another by letter, as well as by word of mouth? I trowe yes. And so God, though hee speakes not now to his church by a created voice, yet by his letter hee speakes to the full, for the cleere manifestation of his will &amp; pleasure, both concerning what he will haue to be beleeued
<pb facs="tcp:177089:30"/>and done by vs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Psal.</hi> 90 <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>Chrysost. in</hi> 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note> For what is the Holy Scripture, but a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or an Epistle sent from God Almighty out of the court of heauen vnto the church militant on earth, to vs his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to instruct vs concerning his will, and to resolue vs in matters of doubt? Now shall we count this instruction and resolution of the Lord by his letter vnsufficient? Wee giue earthly kings leaue to giue definitiue sentence, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in cases by their writing, and though wee neuer heare their voice, yet if we heare or read their writing, we rest sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied concerning their meaning, neither doe we call them dumbe Iudges. And now shall we deny this priviledge to the king of glory, to determine by writing; but wee must blasphemously account him a dumbe Iudge? How doth their speaking Iudge determine all cases in christendome delated vnto him at Rome, but by writing, and bulls, and breues? And yet he scornes to be counted a dumbe Iudge, though he haue no such cause, in respect of true and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgement. And doth not the Lord scorne the scorners of his infallible iudgement by his written word? Yes verily <hi>he scorneth the scorners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3. v. 34.</note> saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> the scorners &amp; moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his written word; and of his sufficient, and cleare iudgement thereby in matters of doubt, and necessary to be knowne and beleeued: And as he scorneth them, So one day,
<note place="margin">Psal. 50. v. 3.4.</note>
                  <hi>Our God shall come, and shall not keepe silence: There shall goe consuming fire before him, and a mighty tempest shall be stirred vp round about him. He shall call the heavens from aboue, and the earth that he may iudge his people. And those his enimies which would not that he should raigne over them,</hi> That is, rule and governe them by his written word; Of them he will say (except they repent) <hi>bring them hither and slay them before me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Thes. 1. v. 7.8.9.</note> Luk. 19.27.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:30"/>
               <head>XLVII That we ought to deny our selues, that is,our owne Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, our owne wills and affections, our owne works and worthinesse; And to follow Christ, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing in him as our only Saviour, &amp; by doing and suffering his will, as our only abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Lord.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord, <hi>Whosoever will follow me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.38. Philip 2.5. Mat. 6.10. Mat. 7.21.</note>
                  <hi>let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himselfe, and follow me. Let the same mind be in you which was also in Christ Iesus. Say thy will be done.</hi> See his will be done by thee and thine, and not thine owne will, <hi>Not the will of the flesh,</hi> 1. Pet. 4.2. Iam. 1.22.</p>
               <p>Learne this in some sort from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> Wee see every member goeth the same way with the head, wherevnto it is vnited, and whereby it is guided: Now Christ is the <hi>spirituall head</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.3.</note>
                  <hi>the head of every man.</hi> And we professe our selues to bee his mysticall body, his members. And so we are indeed, if we follow him as our head and guide, if we take paine to frame and fashion our selues like vnto this head as much as wee can in this life. Otherwise we are not his members; for it is not possible for the head to be of one will, and the members of another. It is not possible that they which are vnited and knit vnto Christ as his members, should not bee touched with a desire to resemble him, and to follow his steps,
<note place="margin">Tho. de Kempis de imitatione Christi in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oemio.</note> for the very thing wherein the <hi>vnion</hi> and <hi>coniunction</hi> are shewed, is that the Members doe shew themselues to bee of the selfe same minde that the head is of. And where that is not done, it is an evident proofe that the member is rotten, senselesse, and void of the life which is in the head. Giue diligence then that <hi>the same minde be in you which was also in Christ Iesus.</hi> Labour that yee may be answerable to him in vnity of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and will. Labour to resemble him in all your whole life: not in his <hi>Miracles,</hi> but in his <hi>Moralls,</hi> his vertues, and
<pb facs="tcp:177089:31"/>godlinesse of liuing. <hi>Whosoever will follow Christ</hi> and be his Disciple, <hi>let him deny himselfe and follow him.</hi> Let the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers follow the direction and guidance of the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="doctrine">
               <head>That parents and all maisters of families should be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to purge and rid their houses of all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and other wilfull and obstinate offenders.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ephes. 5.11.</note>
                  <hi>Haue no fellowship with the vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes of darknesse, but rather reproue them. If any obey not the word, haue no company with him, that he may be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> 2. Thes. 3.14. <hi>If any man that is a brother be a fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, or covetous, or an Idolater, or a drunkard, or an extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or a rayler,</hi> haue no company with him, <hi>with such a one eat not,</hi> saith the Apostle, 1. Cor. 5.11. that is, not so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly and familiarly as with other that feare God: Not with that amitie &amp; delight as with them that excell in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, not if thou beest not bound by reason of cohabitation. Not to countenance him in his sinne. With such a one haue no conversation, or fellowship in this manner. For <hi>what fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship hath righteousnesse with vnrighteousnesse? &amp; what communion hath light with darknesse? and what concord hath Christ with Belial?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. v. 14.15.</note>
                  <hi>or what part hath he that beleeueth with an Infidell?</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> which was a <hi>man after Gods owne heart,</hi> setting downe the forme of his houshold government,
<note place="margin">Psal. 101. ver. 45.6.7.</note> saith thus, <hi>A froward heart shall depart from me, I will not knowe a wicked person, who so privily slandereth his neighbour, him will I cut off: him that hath a high looke, and a proud heart, will not I suffer. Mine eyes shall bee vpon the faithfull of the land, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a godly way, he shall serue me, he that worketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, shall not dwell in my house, he that telleth lyes shall not tarry in my sight.</hi> Thus the Prophet. And this is written for your learning that be maisters of families.</p>
               <p>You may learne this likewise from the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177089:31"/>we see how it is in the <hi>body.</hi> When <hi>Nature</hi> hath any evill, or vnprofitable humours, that oppresseth the <hi>stomacke,</hi> it is fained to cast them out, for the preservation of the health of other parts: So should it be with you; if yee perceiue your families to be endangered by obstinate and obdurate sinners, (as Idolaters, swearers, drunkards, fornicators, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, slanderers, despisers of them that are good, corrupt speakers, <hi>louers of pleasures, or profit, more then louers of God,</hi> and the like) Let it bee your wisdome to vomit them out, as raw and vndigested humours by timely eiection, least the <hi>whole head waxe heauy, and the whole body sickly,</hi> and so the vitall parts languish. A man may catch the plague of his man-servant or his maid-servant, or of some other so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourner within his gates: And now sinne is as infectious as the plague, or rather more, but certainly more dangerous; in that it destroies, not only the body, but the soule also. I say then, as you pray, so let it be your practise;
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> not to lead your selues into temptation; not to thrust your selues wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly into danger. For <hi>hee that loueth danger, shall perish therein, Eccles.</hi> 3.26. <hi>He that toucheth pitch, shall be defiled therewith, Eccles.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="doctrine">
               <head>XLIX That all, both Men and Women,high and low should frame themselues to goe after their place and estate, and to vse that habit or fashion that is meet for them.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. v. 9.</note>
                  <hi>Adorne your selues in modest appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, with shamefastnesse and sobriety. The Woman shall not weare that which pertaineth to the man, neither shall a man put on a womans garment, for all that doe so, are abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lord,</hi> Deut. 22.5. <hi>They that be in Kings Courts, and high places, may weare soft clothing</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> saith, that is,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11. v. 8.</note> silkes and velvets, ornaments of gold, siluer, and pretious stones: So did <hi>Ieseph in Pharaohs Court, Gen.</hi> 41.42. And the <hi>daughter of Pharaoh in Salomons court, Psal.</hi> 45.10. and divers others as wee may read <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.22. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.3.
<pb facs="tcp:177089:32"/>
                  <hi>Hest.</hi> 6.9. But for <hi>persons of low estate,</hi> and meane conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is <hi>not for them to array themselues with broydered haire, or gold, or pearles, or costly apparell,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith, 1 Tim. 2.9. 1 Pet. 3.3. <hi>Every one is to abide in the same calling wherevnto he is called,</hi> saith the same <hi>Apostle,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.20. that is, not only to doe the duty of his proper calling: but to goe and attire himselfe according to his place and calling.</p>
               <p>This also wee may learne out of the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> The <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> haue their severall fashions, which they keepe without incroaching one vpon another. The head hath one fashion, and the foot another, and the necke another, and the backe another, and so the rest of the members haue their severall fashions, whereby they are distinguished one from another. The foot presumes not to put on the habit of the head, or of the necke, or of the hand, but is contented to goe in leather, when it may be, there is a chaine of gold about the necke, and a pretious stone on the finger: Each member is contented to be apparelled and decked with such ornaments and vestures as are most seemely for them: So should it be amongst vs, amongst all sorts of people, in Church and Common-wealth, every one should vse that fashion that belongs to his place, and is fit for him. It is not meet for the <hi>Artificer</hi> to goe clad like the <hi>yeoman,</hi> or the <hi>yeoman</hi> like the <hi>Gentleman;</hi> or the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> as the <hi>Nobleman;</hi> or the <hi>Nobleman</hi> as the <hi>Prince.</hi> It is not fit for <hi>Ioane</hi> to goe as my <hi>Lady;</hi> for the servant to goe as the Master, or M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>, For the meaner &amp; lower sort of people to attire themselues as the higher It is not meet for the foot to put on the habit of the head, or necke. <hi>Leather</hi> is good enough for the <hi>foot.</hi> Neither is fit for the head to put on the habit of the foot. Each member goes attired after his place: And so should every person endeavour to goe after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, place, and calling, to keepe himselfe in his owne order, the higher in their order, &amp; the lower in theirs; Thus Grace and Nature teacheth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:32"/>
               <head>L That wee should not be forward to censure,or to iudge other men.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord. <hi>Iudge not.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.1.</note>
                  <hi>Iudge no man before the time,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. <hi>Who art thou that iudgest another man?</hi> Iam. 4.12.</p>
               <p>We may learne this likewise by the order of Nature. We haue our eyes with eye-lidds to shut them, when our eares are alwaies open; our eares fixed and our eyes moueable; To shew that our eares are to open, to heare the proofe of every tale; and vnmoued, to the end, that though they quickly heare, yet they should not bee moued to censure ouer hastily, <hi>Arist.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="doctrine">
               <head>LI That God is omniscient,and knoweth all things that wee doe speake, or thinke.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written by the Holy <hi>Prophet. O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 139. v. 1.2.3.4.</note>
                  <hi>thou hast Searched mee, and knowne me, thou knowest my downe-sitting, and my vp-rising: thou vnderstandest my thoughts long before, Thou art about my path, and about my bed, and spiest out all my waies. There is not a word in my tongue but thou o Lord, knowest it altogether.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This wee may learne to acknowledge by the <hi>light of Nature,</hi> the eare heareth, and the eye seeth, and the soule vnderstandeth what is done or spoken, and this they doe, being so made of God: Now (to vse the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>he that planted the eare, shall he not heare?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 94. v. 9.10.</note>
                  <hi>Hee that formed the eye, shall hee not see? And he that teacheth man knowledge, shall not he know what is done? and how to punish what is done amisse?</hi> Yes <hi>the Lord knoweth the thoughts of men when they are but vaine, his eyes are in every place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the evill, and the good, Prov.</hi> 15.3. <hi>All things are open, and naked vnto the eyes of him, with whom wee haue to doe,</hi> Heb. 4. <hi>He seeth in secret,</hi> Mat. 6. v. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:33"/>
               <head>LII That the wisdome and power of God in the making and framing of the body of man,is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and praise-worthy.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Holy Prophet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 139. v. 14.</note>
                  <hi>I will praise thee, for I am fearefully and wonderfully made, maruellous are thy workes: and that my soule knoweth right well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this we may know likewise, if we consider the workmanship of our owne bodies, how <hi>Curiously we were wrought in our mothers wombe, in the lowest parts of the earth,</hi> v. 13.15. The body of man rightly Considered in the Composure thereof, is no lesse admirable, then the whole world. For what is man, but a little world (as he is called) that is,
<note place="margin">Tertul de Carne Christi. Jnno cent. de vtilitate Condition. hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> A representation, or Map of the great world? The heauens are represented in the braine; The Sunne in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; The starres in the senses set round about; The Elements in the humors; the riuers in the veynes; the earth in the heart, placed in the middest as a Center; the Sea in the Liuer, from whence the liuely springs of bloud doe flow. Yea <hi>God</hi> the Gouernor of the whole world is represented in man; Euen in his <hi>soule,</hi> being Gods image, as <hi>God</hi> saith, <hi>G.</hi> 1.20. That is a <hi>spirit, immortall, invisible,</hi> as <hi>God</hi> is: Having <hi>three especiall faculties</hi> in one <hi>Nature</hi> as <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> in <hi>one Divine essence;</hi> being <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>body,</hi> as he is <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>world;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 24.</note> Having wisedome, holinesse, righteousnesse, and other graces, as <hi>God</hi> hath for the manner, though not for the measure; being of witty inuention, sound resolution, high and divine contemplation, swift motion, as God is; So swift as shee is able in a moment, to mount vp to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, to descend downe to hell, and to fly to the vttermost parts of the world. So that man may be truly said to be wonderfully made, yea the <hi>abridgment of all wonders,</hi> both in heauen and earth, being an <hi>Epitome</hi> both of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>world,</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in regard of his soule; of the <hi>world,</hi> in the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> of his <hi>body.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:33"/>
               <p>If we goe on farther to the particular parts of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we must needs acknowledge with the holy Prophet, that we are fearefully, and wonderfully made, to the praise of God. To beginne with the <hi>eye:</hi> What an <hi>admirable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> is the eye? Whether we consider the figure, the comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the situation, the motion, or the vse thereof. And the <hi>eare,</hi> how <hi>admirable</hi> is that also, with her windings, and turnings, for the better conveying of the sound to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sense?</hi> For which purpose also is that most artificiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, within the passage of it, as a bell, by repercussion, to continue it to the <hi>Braine:</hi> And more then this, it may pose the <hi>greatest Philosopher</hi> to consider, how the diversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of sounds at the same time reverberating, should so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatly be distinguished; as in a Consort of Musicke, to heare and discerne euery instrument, and also the harmony arising from them.</p>
               <p>Farther, who can sufficiently expresse the singular wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>God</hi> in framing the <hi>Hand?</hi> There are two things, wherein we excell the <hi>beasts, reason</hi> and the <hi>hand,</hi> for as for seeing, hearing, smelling, &amp;c some beasts excell vs; But (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side reason, which is the principall difference) in the hand we doe excell all other bodily creatures. By our reason, and our hand, we gouerne all the creatures vpon earth. Herein we are made more wonderfull then all the rest.</p>
               <p>Vnto these if we adde the differences of constitutions, and countenances, how among the many Millions of men and women in the world, it is almost impossible to find two faces, or temperaments in all things alike, we must needs confesse, that <hi>the body of man is most wonderfully and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But especially if we looke into the inward parts of our bodies, and consider the situation, the figure, the vse and the reason thereof,
<note place="margin">Consult, Platon, in Tim.</note> The <hi>sympathy</hi> betweene the <hi>braine</hi> and the <hi>heart,</hi> and the league, as it were betweene the <hi>stomacke</hi> and the <hi>head,</hi> it cannot but rauish vs with admiration of the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and power of God, such is the admirable composure
<pb facs="tcp:177089:34"/>thereof,
<note place="margin">Arist. De partib animalium. Galen de vsu partii Melanct lib. de anima.</note> that euen learned men haue written <hi>volumes</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Yea and confessed, that there are many <hi>secrets</hi> in mans body, which the most skilfull and curious <hi>Anatomists</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find out, but are onely knowne to God.</p>
               <p>Know thy selfe then <hi>O man,</hi> and (if thou hast not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) seriously consider of thy <hi>Miraculous body,</hi> that thou maiest admire and praise the wisdome and power of thy <hi>God. An vnwise man doth not consider this,</hi> (saith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) <hi>and a foole doth not vnderstand it, Psal.</hi> 92.6. <hi>But Lord how precious are thy thoughts vnto me</hi> (saith he) <hi>how great is the summe of them, Psal.</hi> 139. that is, as if hee had said, Greatly haue I profited in vnderstanding, in comfort, in piety, by thinking on the power, the wisdome, and the providence of God, in framing and preseruing of my body. Now to make an end of this doctrine,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> both of Grace and Nature, I say in the words of Christ, <hi>Goe and doe thou like-wise.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="doctrine">
               <head>LIII That God only is most louely,and loue-worthy.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the word of <hi>truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 45. v. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Thou art fairer then the Children of men. The chiefest among ten thousands,</hi> Cant. 5.10. <hi>What is he among the clouds</hi> (and therefore much lesse among the clods) <hi>that may bee compared vnto the Lord,</hi> Psal. 89.6. <hi>Ʋerily I haue none in Heaven but thee; and there is none in Earth, that I desire in comparison of thee,</hi> saith the Prophet <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 18.1. Psal. 143.6. Psal 119.81.</note> Psal. 73.25. <hi>I loue thee dearely O Lord my God,</hi> saith the same <hi>Prophet, my soule thirsteth after thee, as a thirfly land. My soule longeth for thy salvation. I am sicke of thy loue,</hi> saith the <hi>Church,</hi> Cant. 5.8. This is our part likewise.</p>
               <p>And wee may gather also some helpe out of the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> to be thus affected. By <hi>Nature</hi> we loue, &amp; praise, and desire that which is good; at least which is good in shew and appearance, if not in truth and substance, as sometimes we like of, and commend, and desire that which is faire
<pb facs="tcp:177089:34"/>and beautifull; sometime that which is sweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, sometime him that is honourable; sometime him that is wealthy; sometimes him that is wise: sometimes him that is strong; sometimes him that is vertuous, And so every thing according to his proper goodnesse; and so it is fit we should deeme of Gods creatures, according to that kind and measure of goodnesse which they haue: But if we loue and like the creatures so well, in which there is but a small degree or measure of goodnesse: how much more should wee loue, and magnify the Creator, which is infinitely good, the chiefe good, the fountaine of all goodnesse, the Ocean, wherein the confluence &amp; perfection of all goodnes meet? For what are the beauties, the sweetnesse, the goodnesse, the glory, the pleasures, the graces &amp;c. that appeares in the creatures,
<note place="margin">Splendor sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi idius boni. pulcrum coelum pulchra terra sed pulcrior qui fecitilla.</note> but even <hi>sparkes of that infinite perfection and goodnesse that is in God?</hi> The most <hi>excellent creatures</hi> that are, are but as the <hi>beames</hi> of his beauty. That glory or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse which is in any of them, is but a shadow in respect of that good which is in him, who is the maker of them. The good and the glory that is in the creature is like it selfe, finite, but the glory and the good which is in God, is as he is himselfe, <hi>infinite,</hi> he is all glorious, all good, <hi>in him all fulnesse dwells,</hi> there is nothing louely, &amp; desireable, which is not to be found in him. If wee loue life, he is life, <hi>eternall life;</hi> if wee loue health, he is <hi>health;</hi> if we loue beauty, hee is <hi>beauty;</hi> if wee loue good cheere, he is the <hi>bread of life,</hi> and <hi>water of life;</hi> if wee loue good company, he is <hi>Good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany;</hi> if wee loue peace and quietnesse, hee is the <hi>God of peace;</hi> if wee loue a fine and a faire dwelling place, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is his throne;</hi> if wee loue honour and glory, hee is the <hi>King of glory;</hi> if wee loue riches and treasures, <hi>in him are hid all treasures;</hi> if wee desire ioy and pleasure,
<note place="margin">Psal. 16. vlt.</note>
                  <hi>in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence is the fulnesse of ioy, and at his right hand there are pleasures for evermore.</hi> There is no good, no pleasure, no contentment that can be desired, but is to be found in him, in absolute perfection. What shall wee doe then? What
<pb facs="tcp:177089:35"/>should we doe?
<note place="margin">Colos 3.2</note> but <hi>raise our affections from things that are on earth, and set them on things that are aboue?</hi> On God who only is loue-worthy, in the highest degree. Hauing now seene the faire beauty of the Lord in some sort, and tasted how good,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Si descris illum qui te fecit, &amp; amas illa, quae fecit, adulter es. August. Ac sisponsa plus diligeret accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum annulum quàm sponsum, et diceret sufficit mihi annulus, faciem illius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non deside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro August in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</hi> 2.</note> and gratious the Lord is, it were a most iniurious, and preposterous thing to passe by him who made vs, and to set our loue on those things which he hath made, this were to goe a <hi>whoring from God,</hi> and to play the <hi>adulterer</hi> with his <hi>creatures,</hi> this is to loue the gift more then the giuer: this is as if a new married wife should loue her wedding ring, more then her wedded husband, and should say, now I haue receiued my wedding ring, it is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, I care not, I desire not to see my husbands face any more.</p>
               <p>But not so, O not so, yee sonnes of men, doe not delight in the creature, more then in the Creator, doe not preferre the benefit before the benefactor, the gift before the giver, the shadow before the substance. Rather make you <hi>ladders</hi> of <hi>Gods Creatures,</hi> to climbe vp to heauen, to raise your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections after God. As thus, when yee see the honour, and glory of Princes, consider and say with your selues, how glorious is that God who gaue these their glory? whose servants these are? When ye see the wealth and riches of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; the amiable &amp; louely beauty of others, the wisdome of some men, the stength of others, the sweetnesse of some things, and the fairenesse of others, &amp;c. and so the severall excellencies that be in the creatures; Then consider with your selues and thinke how rich, how beautifull, how wise, how strong, how sweet, how faire that God is, who made all these, so rich, so beautifull, so wise, so strong, so sweet, so faire: and so by this meanes bring thy selfe not to dote vpon the creatures, but to be in loue with God aboue all things: to <hi>count all things but drosse and dung in comparison of him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 3. v. 8.</note> This is the way, walke in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:35"/>
               <head>LIV That wee ought to heare only such things as come from God.</head>
               <p>Thus the Prophet <hi>David.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 85. v. 8. Mat. 17.5.</note>
                  <hi>I will heare what God the Lord will speake.</hi> Thus God the Father by a voice from Heaven saith, <hi>This is my beloued sonne in whom I am well pleased, heare him. He that hath eares to heare, let him heare what the spirit saith.</hi> Revel. 2. <hi>Let him heare the word of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This wee may learne out of the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> The Lord hath made our eares vpright toward Heauen, and why? Even to the end that they should bee open to those things which are of God. But many haue their eares like vnto the eares of those doggs which are closed aboue but open beneath; such are worldlings, who haue an eare to those things which are of the earth, but not to those which are of God. Yea which is worse, an open care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Satan, but a closed eare toward God. But this is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Grace, nor Natures teaching, and so no way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, no way immitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="doctrine">
               <head>LV That wee should be swift to heare and slow to speake.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written, <hi>Be swift to heare, and slow to speake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.19.</note>
                  <hi>hearken, consider, and incline thine eare,</hi> Psal. 45. <hi>But keepe thy mouth as it were with a bridle,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Psal.</hi> 39.2.</p>
               <p>This doctrine likewise we are taught by the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> for God hath giuen vnto man two eares, and one tongue, to teach vs that we should be more ready to heare, then to speake. And God hath set the eares without on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side of the head, continually open: But the tongue he hath placed within the head, and guarded it with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hedge, one of flesh, another of bone, and therewithall hath bound it by a bridle to the brest, by all these recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending vnto vs, a readinesse of hearing, and a moderation of speech.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:36"/>
               <head>LVI That we should ioyne practise and profession together.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord.
<note place="margin">Deut. 6. v. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Heare O Israell and obserue to doe it, that it may be well with thee. Bee doers of the word and not hearers only, deceiuing your selues,</hi> Iam. 1.</p>
               <p>This likewise God hath taught vs, as by his <hi>word,</hi> so by the <hi>worke of Nature.</hi> For as God hath giuen vs eares, eyes and a tongue, so he hath giuen vs hands, and placed these in the body not farre asunder; to teach vs that what wee heare with our eares, and professe with our mouth, wee should practise with our hands, yea God hath giuen vs <hi>two hands</hi> to <hi>one tongue,</hi> to intimate vnto vs, that woe should be greater doers then talkers, greater practisers then professors. It were a monstrous thing to see the mouth of a man bigger then his whole body, or to see a man with a mouth and eares, and no hands: And verily to see the most part of a mans life spent in eating and idle talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his mouth, rather then in doing good with his hands, is no lesse vnseemely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="doctrine">
               <head>LVII That we can never haue a good heart,as long as wee haue a bad tongue, and lead an evill life.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. v. 17.18.</note>
                  <hi>Every good tree bringeth forth good fruit: but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evill fruit. A good tree cannot bring forth evill fruit; neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. Every tree is knowne by his fruit,</hi> and so is every Christian by his words and works, <hi>for out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the heart the mouth speaketh,</hi> yea and the hand moueth. It cannot bee well with the heart when corrupt communication proceeds out of the mouth, or when an evill conversation is led by vs.</p>
               <p>Even reason, and the <hi>light of Nature</hi> is sufficient to make this apparent. For when the <hi>Leprosie</hi> breaketh out in the <hi>face,</hi> it is not an argument that the bloud is foule and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected?
<pb facs="tcp:177089:36"/>And when the smoake bursts forth at the doores, &amp; windowes, is it not a token that the house is full of smoke within? So it is in the <hi>state of man,</hi> when filthinesse breakes out into the mouth, the eye, and hand, it is an vndoubted argument of superabundant corruption in the heart: O What a filthy heart hath he, who even by his breath infects such as are neere to heare him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="doctrine">
               <head>LVIII That wee should not abuse our tongues to the dishonour of God by swearing,or to the defaming of men by slandering, or any kinde of evill speaking.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>Keepethy tongue from evill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.11. Iam. 5.14.</note>
                  <hi>and thy lipps that they speake no guile. Be fore all things sweare not, neither by Heaven, neither by Earth, neither by any other oathes, but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, least ye fall into condemnation, see you speake not evill one of another.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.11.</note>
                  <hi>Put away all filthy speaking out of your mouth,</hi> Colos. 3.8.</p>
               <p>Learne this likewise out of the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> When the <hi>Palsie</hi> or <hi>Convulsion</hi> causeth the members of the body, to moue against the will of him that possesseth them, as the face or mouth to writh about, it is counted a pittifull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease, and vnpleasant to looke vpon: So it is when the <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Palsie,</hi> or convulsion of sinne causeth them to moue against the will of him that made them, and the will of them that owe them: this is an evill disease, yea and a sore evill, such an evill as tends to the second death, howsoever many make light of it, and reioyce in it. Is it not an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing sight to see a mans mouth turned awrie? And the head drawne backward to the backe and shoulders? Such, and much more vnseemely is his griefe and infirmity, who turnes his mouth from glorifying of God, and edifying his neighbour, to the dishonouring of God by swearing and cursed speaking, &amp; the slaundering of his neighbour by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill speaking; such a ones mouth is turned awrie, his face stands backward. Now if any swearing, lying, railing, and
<pb facs="tcp:177089:37"/>reviling companion will not beleeue this, I say noe more, but what Phisitians vse to say to their patients in the like kinde; That is, let them behold themselues in a glasse, I meane the glasse of Gods word. And then I doubt not, but they will quickly discerne their wrie mouth, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart face, and I hope have the grace and strength to turne them aright.</p>
               <p>And verily if we goe no farther then the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> we may learne so to rectify our tongues as wee be not dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tongued, or dissemblers in our speech. For God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven man but one tongue, to teach him not to be <hi>bilinguis,</hi> or double tongued. And he hath seated the Lungs, the bellowes of the voice, very neere the heart, to teach vs, that our <hi>speech</hi> should bee the interpreter of our hearts; and that wee should not thinke one thing and speake another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="doctrine">
               <head>LIX That we should not open our eyes to every obiect.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">Prou. 4. v. 25. Psal. 119. v. 37.</note>
                  <hi>Let thine eyes looke right on, and let thine eye-lidds looke straight before thee. Turne away thine eyes from beholding vanity, make a covenant with thine eyes,</hi> Iob. 31. <hi>Set the Lord alwaies before thine eyes,</hi> Psal. 16.8. <hi>Shut them from seeing evill.</hi> Esa. 33.15.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>Nature</hi> teacheth vs. <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Nature</hi> hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a covering for the <hi>eye,</hi> which with a marvelous volubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity openeth and closeth at the pleasure of man; wherein the Lord, who hath done all his workes in great wisedome, hath warned vs, that it is expedient sometimes that the eye be closed and not holden open to euery obiect.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt qui exteriori negligent er vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oculo, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riori non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuste Caecetur Gregor. Moral. lib.</hi> 21.</note> When the eye lies open to every obiect, there is great danger in it, for oftentimes it comes to passe, by a most iust recompence, that <hi>he whone gligently vseth the exterior eye, should iustly be blinded in the interior.</hi> So was <hi>Sichem</hi> looking with wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eyes after <hi>Dinah,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> looking after <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> and <hi>Achan</hi> looking after the <hi>wedge of gold,</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the forbidden fruit: All of these were ensnared
<pb facs="tcp:177089:37"/>for looking negligently with their eyes, and suffering them to wander. And no marvell, for if a man having his house, hardly beset with strong enemies, doth set open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and doores vnto them to enter in, is it any great wonder, if he be surprised, and taken, and robbed of his goods, whenas he betraies himselfe into their hands? And such is our case. <hi>Satan</hi> the great and strong enimy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, laies continuall <hi>siege</hi> to the <hi>Castle of our soules,</hi> with all his forces and policies, sometimes by inward suggestions,
<note place="margin">Animae sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strae. August.</note> but most commonly by outward incursions vpon the doores and windowes of our soules, the senses; and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the eyes and eares, presenting vnwarrantable obiects therevnto. And now if wee set wide open these doores, and windowes of our soules, the senses, and namely the eyes, how shall wee thinke to escape surprisall, and ensnaring by the Divell? Wee cannot. <hi>Eue</hi> in her innocency could not doe it, much lesse can we doe it. And therefore looke to the doores and windowes of thy soule, locke them, barre them, bolt them fast, that the Divell enter not that way. Make vse of that which God in Nature hath provided, and close thine eyes: or at least turne them away from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanity, &amp; feed them with warrantable obiects, as 1 God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Taylor exposit. in tempt Christi p.</hi> 294.</note> 2 his word, 3 the creatures, 4 thy brethren, 5 thy selfe. Let thine eyes delight in the waies of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="doctrine">
               <head>LX That we should bee very carefull to keepe,and preserue our spirituall sight, the eye of faith from any hurt or blemish.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>Contend earnestly for the faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. c. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Rebuke them sharply that they may be sound in the faith,</hi> Tit. 1.13. <hi>Stand fast in the faith,</hi> 1. Cor. 16.13. <hi>Keepe as thine heart, so thine eye</hi> of faith, super omnem Custodiam, <hi>with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> exhorts Prou. 4.23.</p>
               <p>Learne this likewise from the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> If the <hi>eye</hi> be once offended with the smallest mote, we delay not
<pb facs="tcp:177089:38"/>to remedie it, but doe implore the helpe of such as are nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest vs to take it out. Now since by Nature we are so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to keepe the eye, by which we see the Sunne, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full should we be, to conserue the <hi>eye,</hi> by which we see him, who made the sunne? Especialy seeing if it be hurt we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see him therewith.
<note place="margin">Non solum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit se à luce, sed etiam poe natis illi fit lux: Sic &amp; oculis cor dis perturbatus &amp; sauciatus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit se à iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiae lumine, nec audit eam contemplari nec valet.</note> For, <hi>as the eye of the body, if it be hurt and wounded, doth not onely turne away from beholding the light, but the light also which otherwise is delightfull becomes dainefull to it: So the eye of the soule being hurt and troubled, turnes it selfe away from the light of righteousnesse, neither dare it, neither can it behold it.</hi> As therefore we are tender of the <hi>eye</hi> of the <hi>body:</hi> so, &amp; much more let vs be tender of the <hi>eye</hi> of the soule, eschewing Carefully the euill that may hurt it; and esteeming much of the good that may preserue it. The euill that may hurt it, is either the <hi>mucke of the world,</hi> or our owne <hi>grosse</hi> and <hi>carnall affections.</hi> For as the bodily sight is <hi>two manners of wayes offended;</hi> either by <hi>exterior dust</hi> cast into it; or by <hi>interior humours</hi> stopping the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke nerues</hi> within: So the <hi>spirituall sight</hi> is also <hi>two waies</hi> offended, that is, either by <hi>Sathans</hi> casting into our eyes the <hi>dongue of the world</hi> therewith to blind vs; or else by our own grosse and carnall affections, stopping the <hi>conduits</hi> of our <hi>sight,</hi> that we cannot see the Lord: So that if we will eschew the evill that may hurt it, we must eschew both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>And againe if we will esteeme of the good which may helpe and <hi>preserue our spirituall sight,</hi> then we must esteeme of the <hi>light of Gods word,</hi> of hauing some <hi>conformity with God in holinesse.</hi> And we must giue diligence that our hearts be stablished by attention, and consideration.</p>
               <p>First we must esteeme of the <hi>light of Gods word.</hi> For as the eye cannot see without the light of the sunne: no more cannot we see the Lord by the eye of faith, without the light of Gods word.</p>
               <p>Neither can wee see him without some <hi>conformity</hi> with him in holinesse: for as no <hi>member</hi> in the body can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
<pb facs="tcp:177089:38"/>the light of the sunne but the <hi>Eye,</hi> by reason of a simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude which is betweene them: so can no man see the Lord except in some measure hee bee like him in purenesse and holinesse, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>And lastly he must haue a <hi>heart stablished</hi> by attention &amp; consideration that will see the Lord; For as a tumbling and a rowling eye seeth not those things which are before it: so a wandring minde not stablished by consideration and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine contemplation cannot see the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXI. That we should abhorre idlenesse,and every one walke in a lawfull calling, endeauouring to doe the best good we can with the gifts which God hath given vs.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>Be not slothfull in businesse.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 12. v. 11. Mat. 20.6.</note>
                  <hi>Why stand yee all the day idle? Goe and labour in the Ʋineyard. Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one abide in the calling wherein he is placed. At every man hath receaued the gift, so let him minister the same one to another. Let him occupie therewith till I come,</hi> saith Christ Luk. 19, 13.</p>
               <p>And as God in his word, so God in nature hath warned vs hereof. God hath made no dead or idle member in the naturall body, but every one actrue, and doing in his place and kinde. The head and the rest of the superior and more honourable parts, these are made to bee serviceable one to another, and for the good of the whole, as well as the feet &amp; the rest of the inferiour members; yea and they doe service as much, if not more then the inferiour members, there is no member idle. The head watcheth and looketh out for the safety and welfare of the inferiour members, the Eate hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, the Tongue speakes, the Nose smels, the Hand workes, the feet walke; All the members are stirring and in action one for another, and for the good of the whole. This is to reach vs to employ our selues in some lawfull calling, either in the Church, Common-wealth, or family, wherein wee
<pb facs="tcp:177089:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177089:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177089:40"/>may doe good, and not to spend our time, and the talents which God hath giuen vs, idly, wantonly, vpon our lusts, after the evill example of the world, or yet to hide them so, as to doe no good with them.</p>
               <p>They that haue receaued life, and health, and liberty, and maintenance, and knowledge, and power, &amp; ability to doe good, and doe it not, such are not worthy to be called liuing men or women, but rather Idols or images of men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:
<note place="margin">Psal. 115. v. 5.6.7.</note> in that <hi>they haue cares and heare not, eyes and see not, mouthes and speake not, noses and smell not, hands and handle not, feet and walke not</hi> in the waies of the Lord. Liuing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are mouing and stirring bodies, and haue the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of motion in themselues, they moue and stirre in all their parts and faculties: &amp; so it is with the parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the mysticall body of Christ, the Church. they be all liuing, and moving, and stirring in good motions and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actions.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> Yea and they moue <hi>not of constraint but of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy minde,</hi> 1. Pet. 5.2. So then if you will hearken and learne either of <hi>Grace</hi> or <hi>Nature, Bee not sloathfull in the businesse of the Lord,</hi> lead not an idle and vnprofitable life, making an ill vse, or no vse of the gifts and talents which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you, but imploy your felues in some lawfull calling, &amp; doe good with your talents while you haue time. Brests not often drawne, will so one dry vp: and so gifts not well vsed, will soone abate and cause the Lord to leaue vs, and to bereaue vs of his gifts and graces. But if a member be putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and quite dead, we vse to cut it off: And so will the Lord deale at last with all vnprofitable servants, who make an ill vse, or no good vse of the gifts which God hath giue them, He will cut, he will cast them off into vtter darknesse, when the profitable and faithfull ones shall enter into their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters ioy, Mat. 25.30, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:40"/>
               <head>LXII That the greater our zeale, paines, and travell hath beene, is,or shall be in Gods cause, the greater shall be the waight of our glory.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">Psal. 62.12. Gal. 6.7. 2. Cor. 9.6. Mat. 19. v. 28.</note>
                  <hi>God will reward every man according to his workes. As a man soweth so shall he reap, hee that sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth liberally shall reape liberally.</hi> The <hi>twelue Apostles</hi> shall haue <hi>twelue especiall thrones</hi> at the day of iudgement, and whereas otherwise men shall shine, but with the brightnesse of the Firmament, <hi>they that turne others from their wicked waies vnto righteousnesse, shall shine as the starres in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament,</hi> Dan. 12.3.</p>
               <p>It is here somewhat as it is in <hi>Nature.</hi> In <hi>Nature</hi> the sleepe of him that hath passed the day more easily, is sweet, but the sleepe of the labouring man is sweet indeed. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so though the sleepe in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bosome be sweete, even to such as haue liued a more quiet and easie life here, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven there also, the sleepe of the <hi>labourer</hi> will bee specially sweet. The greater our toile and trialls haue beene, the more we haue sweat and suffered here for Christ, the swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter shall wee finde that rest and repose in heauen: And this not because of our merit, but because God is mercifull, So saith the Prophet, <hi>Thou Lord art mercifull, for thou reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est every man according to his worke, Psal.</hi> 62.12. So then, in as much as the more grace wee shew here, the more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wee shall finde hereafter, I say with the Apostle,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. v. 5.8.</note>
                  <hi>My beloued brethren, be stedfast, vnmoueable, alwaies abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the worke of the Lord, for as much as you know that your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXIII That wee should not be disheartned from doing the duties of our calling because wee cannot worke that good which wee desire.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the word of Crace. <hi>Be not weary of well doing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177089:41"/>
                  <hi>stand fast in the faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Thes. 3.12. 2 Chron. 15. v. 7.</note>
                  <hi>and play the men, be strong</hi> 1 Cor. 16.13. Take courage to you and persevere to the end. Thus Saint <hi>Paul, who shall separate mee from the loue of God in Christ? Shall tribulation, or distresse, or perseeution, or famine, or nakednesse, or perill or sword? No. Neither death, nor life, nor Angells, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come, nor height, nor dopth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, shall be able to separate vs from the loue of God which is in Christ Iesus our Lord, Rom.</hi> 8.35.36.37.38. And what he there professed, hee afterward performed according to that, <hi>I haue fought the good fight, I haue finished my course,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7.8. And this is our duty likewise.</p>
               <p>And this wee may learne from the course of Nature. The <hi>Physitian</hi> omits no point of his art, though the recouery of his Patient seeme desperate. And so, though wee preach to many desperate and scoffing hearers. yet wee must not giue over, but giue the more diligence. The <hi>Phisitian</hi> hath his see, whether he recouer his patient or not: And so whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our hearers profit by vs or no, wee shall haue our fee. <hi>Whether our preaching be the savour of life vnto life, or of death vnto death vnto them, wee are a sweet savour vnto God in them,</hi> 2 Cor 2. v. 15. <hi>Our worke is with the Lord,</hi> Isa. 44 4. and the Lord of his mercy will reward it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 66. <hi>vlt.</hi> Though our labour be sometime in vaine with men, yet it is <hi>never in vaine in the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. vlt.</note> wee shall not loose our labour with him, though sometime wee loose it with men. <hi>The Lord will reward every man according to his worke,</hi> saith the Prophet; Not according to the fruit and successe of his worke, but according to his worke; if the successe faile, man shall not faile of his reward, for the successe of our worke is not ours, but Gods worke. Our worke is to doe the will of him that sent vs, to performe the duties of our callings wherein hee hath placed vs; but to giue good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse to our workes, that is Gods worke, not ours; When <hi>Paul</hi> hath <hi>planted,</hi> and <hi>Apollo watered, it is God that must giue the increase.</hi> So then let no man bee discouraged or
<pb facs="tcp:177089:41"/>disheartned from a diligent and constant performing of the duties of his calling, though he see little, or no good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse thereof. Let vs doe our worke, that which belongs to vs, with an honest and good heart, and let God alone with his worke, the successe thereof. Whatsoever the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse is on earth, small or great, assuredly the reward is great in Heauen, if wee performe the duty required, with a perfect heart, and a willing minde. Nay the lesse the successe, the greater shall be the reward, so thou be patient; for now vnto thy actiue obedience in well doing, thou addest passiue, in patient suffering; and double obedience, must needs haue more then a single reward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXIIII That we should not goe beyond our gifts.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12. v. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Let no man thinke of himselfe more highly then he ought to thinke, but thinke soberly according as God hath dealt to every man the measure of faith. Professe not the knowledge which thou hast not</hi> saith the wiseman, Ecclesi. 2.25. And this was obserued by <hi>Dauid,</hi> according to that saying of his,
<note place="margin">Psal. 131. v. 2.3. 3.</note>
                  <hi>I doe not exercise my selfe in great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which are too high for me, but I refraine my selfe.</hi> This is our part likewise.</p>
               <p>And this the <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> will teach vs. The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body as long as they be sound and whole, doe not exceed their due proportion: if any of the limbs doe swell and waxe over big, it is not beautifull or comely, it is no signe of health in the body, but rather of a dropsie, or of some disease: So it is in the Mysticall body of Christ the Church: They that be sound members thereof thinke and speake soberly, according to the measure dealt vnto them, and containe themselues within their bounds, Discoursing modestly of God and his Mysteries, and in some things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content to be ignorant, thinking others to be as learned as themselues. But they that be weake, and are of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound mind, they most commonly swell, and their tongue
<pb facs="tcp:177089:42"/>is too bigge for their mouth;
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.6.7.</note> they are full of <hi>vaine iangling;</hi> teachers they would faine be, though they vnderstand nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what they say, nor whereof they affirme. But if wee will shew our selues to be sound members, and of a sound minde, let vs consider our proportion of gifts receaued, and hold our selues there. If a man eate of wholsome meate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and according to the proportion of his naturall heate, it turnes to good nutriment, but if he over charge his stomacke, &amp; the naturall heate be not able to concoct it, it turnes to putrifaction: so it is with them which greedily fearch into matters aboue their gifts. Or as a burden beyond the proportion of our strength oppresleth the body: so a searching into points, beyond the proportion of our gift to conceaue,
<note place="margin">Pro. 25. v. 16.</note> overwhelmeth the vnderstanding: it doth not better our knowledge, but decay it. As then <hi>Solomon</hi> said of hony, <hi>eate not too much hony:</hi> so I say, be not too immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in prying into the hidden things of God, though they be sweet and comfortable in themselues; wade not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thy height. Every man cannot fathom or sound that depth of predestination, yea, I thinke no man can sound out the true depth of it:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. v. 2.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> who was rapt vp into the third heauen, and saw a great deale more then any man now sees,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.1.33.</note> yet could not fully see it, and finde it out by his owne confession, much lesse can any of vs. Neither hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man a gift to vnderstand the doctrine of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to iudge of controversies: I say then againe, let every one examine the measure of Gods gifts bestowed on him, and so apply himselfe: As in reading and studying the Scriptures, read and studie such things specially which God hath enabled thee to conceaue and vnderstand. If thou meet with difficult and hard things, passing thy capacity, tire not thy selfe about them, let them alone: Beleeue that to be true which is written, though thy gift will not serue thee to see the reason of it. If any mans ability and gifts will serue him to travell in the controverted points of predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, freewill, Church-governments, &amp;c. he may: but still
<pb facs="tcp:177089:42"/>let him not forget to <hi>thinke soberly, according to the measure dealt vnto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A man that goes to the brooke for water, can bring no more then his Pitcher will hold: Now consider thy Pitcher, lest whilst thou goest about to vnderstand aboue thy gift, thou bring to passe <hi>(vt minimum intelligendo nihil intelligas)</hi> that thou proue thy selfe a very dolt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXV That Parents should accommodate their Children to a fit Calling.</head>
               <p>Thus <hi>Adam</hi> our first Father, he placed his sonnes,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4. v 2.</note>
                  <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> in a lawfull calling, and he fitted their callings to their inclinations, and the naturall gifts of body and mind, which they had being children, making the one, <hi>a keeper of sheepe,</hi> to wit <hi>Abel;</hi> and the other <hi>a tiller of the ground,</hi> even <hi>Caine.</hi> This care of making choice of fit callings for their children, both in respect of inclination, and naturall gifts, belongs vnto all good Parents.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Natures light</hi> will make plaine. When the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body are out of their proper places, what readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is in them to doe any worke or service? surely none. And verily, when a man is out of his proper calling in any society, it is, as if a member were out of ioynt in the body, there is no pleasure in it: it is no kindnesse, but a great wrong to children, and the society of men, to be so dislocated or put out of ioynt. To make thy sonne a Tradesman, if he be most fit for learning; or contrariwise to apply him to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when he is fittest for a Trade; or to send him to the Court, when he is fittest for the Cart, this is as much as if a man should apply his toes to feeling, and not his fingers, and should walke on his hands, and not on his feere,
<note place="margin">Sir George Paul in the life of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift. p. 85.</note> which is neuer like to doe well. It was a memorable fact of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Bishop of Lincolne, <hi>Robert Grosted,</hi> who being vpon a time solicited to preferre his poore kinsman, and therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inquiring what condition of life he followed, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb facs="tcp:177089:43"/>that he was a Husbandman. Why then (answered he) if his plow be broken, I will repaire it; or rather then faile bestow a new vpon him, whereby he may goe on his course: but to dignifie him, as to make him forsake his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and trade wherein he was brought vp, I meane not to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXVI That ignorance is the cause of sinne,and also of most fearfull destruction.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written. <hi>The people haue erred in their hearts, for they haue not knowne my waies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 95.</note>
                  <hi>Yee erre not knowing the Scriptures. My people are destroyed for lacke of knowledge,</hi> Hos. 4.6.
<note place="margin">Mat. 22. v. 29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This the Booke of Nature will teach vs to acknowledg. <hi>A body destitute of eyes</hi> cannot discerne the day from the night, a friend from a foe, nor the pit from the plaine: No more can a darkned mind diseerne the manifold snares of Sathan; but as our Saviour saith, <hi>where the blind leads the blind,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note>
                  <hi>both of them must at length fall into the ditch:</hi> So where a blinded mind is the director of a corrupted will, what can the end be but fearfull destruction? Wherefore I say with the Apostle, <hi>Be not vnwise but vnderstand what the will of the Lord is,</hi> Ephes. 5.17. <hi>Wisdome is the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall thing therefore get Wisdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 4 27.</note>
                  <hi>and with all thy get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, get vnderstanding.</hi> A man without vnderstanding and knowledge of the word of God, is as a man without eyes, in continuall danger to be misled: Yea he is in worse case, and in greater dauger, then he that wants his naturall sight:
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.46.47.</note> for a man may want his naturall sight, and yet come vnto Christ, as blind <hi>Bartimeus</hi> did. But if he want the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall sight, (which is the knowledge of Gods truth) hee cannot come vnto Christ,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. v. 5. 1. Tim. 2.4.</note> he cannot know the way as <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> said. <hi>They that come vnto him to be saued, must first come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> saith. <hi>Qui ea quae sunt Domini nesciunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gregor in past. crat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>a Domino nesciuntur,</hi> They that know not the things of the Lord, shall not be knowne
<pb facs="tcp:177089:43"/>of the Lord. <hi>The Lordshall appeare in flaming fire to render vengeance vnto all them that know him not, and that obey not his Gospell,</hi> 2 Thes. 5.7.8.9. Giue diligence then to <hi>know the God of thy Father, and to sorue him with a perfect heart, and a willing mind,</hi> as holy <hi>David</hi> giues counsell, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXVII That wee should bee very carefull that we doe not wittingly and willingly offend against the checks of conscience,and the cleere light of Gods word.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Word of Truth.
<note place="margin">Deut. 29. v. 19 20.</note>
                  <hi>If a man will turne away from the Lord his God, and goe on wilfully and serue sinne, blessing himselfe in his heart, and saying I shall haue peace, though I walke in the imagination of mine heart, to adde drunkenesse to thirst, The Lord will not spare him, but the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord, and his iealousie shall smoake against that man, and all the curses that are written in the booke of the Law, shall lye vpon him, and the Lord shall blot out his name from vnder Heaven.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal 29 v. 5. Heb. 1026.27.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord will not be mercifull vnto him that offendeth of malicious wickednesse. If wee sinne wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, after that wee haue receiued the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more sacrifice for sinne, but a certaine fearfull looking for of iudgement, and fiery indignation which shall devoure the adversaries.</hi> Remember then that you <hi>harden not your hearts</hi> against the voice of the Lord, <hi>as in the provocation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The very <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> will shew the danger of this to be great For whē the patient loaths his food, quarrels with his phisitian, is angry with his friends, chafes with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, In reason you will say he is in an ill case. And such is the Condition of a froward, and malitious sinner that will hearken to no good counsell, but scorne &amp; reject it. He is in a desperate case. When the <hi>vis irascibilis</hi> which should be as a dogge at the doore of the soule to keepe away the theefe, shall waxe mad and bite his master, or his friends,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:44"/>and even snarle at God, at his servants, and his sacred truth. What safety, what comfort can that soule haue? Surely none. When the patient rejects the meanes of his recouery, what hope of safety can there be?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXVIII That we should not venture vpon the committing of any the least sinne,vpon presumption of Gods mercy, or in hope of future repentance.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.1, 2. Psal. 130. v. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Shall we continue in sinne, because grace doth abound? God forbid. There is mercie with God that he may be feared,</hi> saith David. Not that he should be neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; haue his cōmandements slighted, but that he might be feared and obeyed. <hi>The grace of God teacheth vs,</hi> not to liue in sinne, <hi>but to denie all vngodlinesse, and worldly lusts, and to liue soberly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note>
                  <hi>righteously, and godly in this present world, as Saint Paul</hi> saith. Yea and to doe this without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes,
<note place="margin">Eccles. 12. v. 1. Prou. 27. v. 1. Psal. 119. v. 90.</note> so it is written, <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, before the evill dayes come. Boast not thy selfe of to morrow, for thou knowest not what a day will bring forth. I made hast and prolonged not the time to keepe Gods righteous iudgments</hi> saith <hi>Dauid.</hi> And this is our part likewise.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> will teach vs better wisdome, then to Presume to commit the least sinne, because God is is mercifull, or that Christ died for sinners. For if a man should breake his owne head, because he hath a <hi>plaster,</hi> or surfet because he hath a <hi>Phisitian,</hi> or take some deadly poyson because he hath good <hi>Mithridate;</hi> Would any man commend his wisdome? Would not euery one condemne him of grosse foolishnesse? And now such a one is he, who wounds, or poysons his soule and conscience with sinne, because of Gods mercie. For euery sinne is a wound to the soule, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very sinfull motion is a poyson to it, yea and a deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6. v. 23.</note> For <hi>the wages of sin is death.</hi> If you be wise then, doe not take the deadly poyson of sinne into your minds, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so little, in hope of the <hi>Mithridate</hi> of Christs passion
<pb facs="tcp:177089:44"/>to heale it. You will not willingly wound your selues, that you may goe to the <hi>Chirurgian:</hi> And noe more doe you sinne in your youth, that you may sue for pardon in your old age. <hi>Gods mercie,</hi> and Christs merit, is a soveraigne salue for all sores, of sinne, but it is effectuall <hi>to those that feare him, throughout all generations,</hi> as the scripture saith, Luk.
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.50.</note> 1.50.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXIX That wee must take speciall heed of recidination,or falling into the same sinne againe, after wee haue once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented thereof and forsaken it.</head>
               <p>Thus faith the Lord. <hi>If any man draw backe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. v. 38.</note>
                  <hi>my soule shall haue no pleasure in him. He that puteth his hand to the plough</hi> (that is to the profession and practise of Christianity) <hi>and looketh backe, is not fit for the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.62. Psal. 18.22.</note> saith Christ. <hi>The Lord will tread downe revolters vnder his feete, as clay in the streets,</hi> saith <hi>David.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. v. 20.</note>
                  <hi>If after they haue escaped the pollutions of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord, and Saviour Iesus Christ, they are againe intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled therein, and overcome; the latter end is worse with them then the beginning,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Peter. Be not then of them, who draw backe vnto perdition, but of them that beleeue to the sauing of the soule,</hi> Heb. 9.39.</p>
               <p>Learne of <hi>Nature,</hi> when thou hast fasted for thy sinnes,
<note place="margin">Eccles. 34. v. 26.</note> not to commit them againe, not to runne in the same ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of riot: if one hauing recouered his health, fall againe into the relapse of his former disease, whether it be of an ague, or some other strong disease, hee is in more danger then he was before; his recouery is a great deale the harder, and his life in danger: So it is with a man, who after repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for some grievous sinne falls into the same againe, his sicknesse of sinne is a great deale the more dangerous, and his recovery much more vnlikely. The bone often bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kē will hardly be set. The tree oft trans-planted will scarcely prosper: and no more will he that is often moued from his
<pb facs="tcp:177089:45"/>owne stedfastnesse. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith that <hi>the latter end of such, is worse then the beginning,</hi> 2. Pet. 2.20. looke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to your standing, and take heede least ye fall Art thou made whole? <hi>Sinne no more least a worse thing fall vnto thee,</hi> Ioh. 5 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXX That we should not iudge of them as Reprobates,or Cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awaies, who hauing professed Christ &amp; his religion, afterward fall there from in time of persecution, or some strong temptation.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord.
<note place="margin">Mat. 7 1. 1 Cor. 4.5.</note>
                  <hi>Iudge not. Iudge no man before the time.</hi> Iudge not the <hi>Iewes</hi> that fell, <hi>for they bide not still in vnbeleefe, shall be grafted in: for God is able to graft them in againe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. v. 23.</note> as the Apostle saith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>And wee haue some shew for this out of the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> A man may recouer his health after a relapse into some strong disease, so many haue recouered after a relapse into an ague, or some other disease. Wee read of some that recouered after <hi>twelue yeares sicknesse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 9 20. Luk. 13.11. Ioh. 5.5.</note> as the woman with the bloudy issue: of other that recouered after <hi>eighteene yeares</hi> infirmity: and of other that recouered after <hi>eight and thirty yeares</hi> sicknesse: and some of <hi>forty yeares,</hi> Act. 4.22. Yea wee read of some that got vp, after they were sicke, and dead,
<note place="margin">Luk. 8.5 5. Luk. 7.11. Ioh. 11.44.</note> and buried, and stunke in the graue, as <hi>Iairus</hi> daughter, the <hi>Widdowes</hi> sonne, and <hi>Lazarus:</hi> The one new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead, the other dead and wound vp, and lying vpon the hearse, and the third, dead, buried, and stinking in the graue, and yet all recouered, got vp, and well, by the help of that good, and Soveraigne Phisitian Christ Iesus.</p>
               <p>And so may a man or woman recouer their soules health, after a long &amp; tedious sicknesse in sinne, yea after a relapse into sinne.
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 33.3.</note>
                  <hi>Manasses</hi> recouered, and was receiued to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, after he fell to idolatry and witcheraft. So was <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> after his falling away, witnesse his penning of some parts of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> as the <hi>Proverbs, Ecclesiastes,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:177089:45"/>
                  <hi>Song of Songs,</hi> but especially <hi>Ecclesiastes,</hi> the booke of his repentance. And so againe <hi>Peter</hi> after hee had denyed his Master Christ, of knowledge, against his owne conscience, and that with cursing and banning, yet he recouered, and came to repentance afterwards, and obtained mercy, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by that saying of Christ vnto him. <hi>I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not, therefore when thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, strengthen thy brethren,</hi> Luk. 22.32.</p>
               <p>And why should we iudge of any man as a reprobate, or castaway, though he be in great fault, &amp; doe liue in sinne? <hi>What haue I to iudge them that are without,</hi> saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Paul?</hi> Much lesse may wee iudge them that are within the visible Church, and liue vnder the meanes of their conversion, that is, the Ministry of Gods word. Why? Is not God as well able to heale the soule, as to cure the body of whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever disease it hath? Is not he now able to make of <hi>Saul</hi> a <hi>Paul,</hi> of an <hi>Apostate</hi> an <hi>Apostle,</hi> as well as ever hee was? Yes verily, <hi>his hand is not shortned that he cannot saue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Esa. 50.2. Esa. 59.1. Mat. 11.</note> as the Prophet saith, he is still able, and willing to helpe, and to heale vs of whatsoever disease wee haue in soule or body, if wee come vnto him with vnfained repentance of sinnes past, with sound faith in the merits of Christ for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of those sinnes, and with earnest and fervent prayer for the obtaining of that pardon, and for grace to part with our sinne, and to amend our liues.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6. v. 37. Mat. 9.13. 1. Tim. 1. v. 15. Mat. 18. v. 11.</note>
                  <hi>He that cometh vnto me</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>I will in no wise cast off. I am come into the world to call sinners to repentance, to saue sinners, to saue them that are lost. God sent not his sonne into the world to condemne the world, but that the world through him might be saved,</hi> saith Christ himselfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudge no man then</hi> (I say with the Apostle) <hi>before the time,</hi> I meane touching his finall estate,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. v. 5.</note> as that such a one is a castaway. Tis true, we may and that lawfully judge of a mans present estate, as whether hee be sicke in body or in soule, whether he brings forth good fruit, or bad fruit, or no fruit: But to say (by reason of present barrennesse) <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:177089:46"/>fruit grow on thee any more,</hi> that is beyond our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and our commission, that science and that sentence belongs to Christ and not to vs.
<note place="margin">Mat. 21. v. 19.</note> He that to day is desperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sicke both in body and soule, may to morrow be well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for all that wee know, and so I desire of the Lord Iesus that they may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXXI That we should not make the sinnes and infirmities,or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of other men, a matter of our mirth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, but our sorrow and heauinesse.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Lord.
<note place="margin">Prou. 24. v. 17.18.</note>
                  <hi>Reioyce not when thine enemie fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: and let not thine heart be glad when he stumbleth, least the Lord see it, and it displease him, and he turne away his wrath from him. The children of God neuer made themselues merry with the infirmities, and miseries of other men, but grieued at it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 119. v. 53. Ier. 13. v. 17.</note> thus Dauid, <hi>mine eyes gush out with water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause men keep not thy law:</hi> thus Ieremie, <hi>If yee will not heare, my soule shall weepe in secret places for your pride, and mine eye shall weepe sore, and runne downe with teares, because the Lords flock is carried away captiue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9. v 2.</note> So Paul, <hi>I haue great hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinesse and continuall sorrow in my heart for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh,</hi> the vnbeleeuing and disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Iewes, and thus other of the saints of God, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 94. And this is our part not to reioyce, but to grieue at the infirmities and calamities of men in the world.</p>
               <p>And this we may learne even from <hi>Natures</hi> teaching For if thou shouldest see a man grievously wounded, fetching deadly grones, and drawing his last breth, would not even <hi>Nature</hi> constraine thee to be sorry to see it, and not to make a sport and a pastime thereof? How much lesse shouldst thou reioyce when thou seest thy brother or thy neighbour, wounding and stabbing himselfe, even to the heart, by his abominable sinnes? As blasphemies, prophanesse, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp;c. how should this wring even teares of blood from thee, rather then a laughter? We lament ouer the bodies of
<pb facs="tcp:177089:46"/>our friends, which we beleeue shall be raised to glory at the last day. How much more should we mourne and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer the soules of men, which goe downe vnder the power of everlasting death? Well, if thou hast any grace in thee, it will constraine thee to lament for this; as Nature moues thee to mourne for the other. The Prophets, and the Apostles, who had true grace, did grieue for the sinnes and miseries of the people, and so did Christ himselfe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.33. Be you followers herein. When thou seest sinners in words, or behaviour to be out of the way, if thou couldst insteed of a smile, afford a teare, thy teare might happly make them relent, when thy smile confirmeth them in their wickednesse. For as many times the seeing of others fall heartily to their meat, brings on our stomacke: so the sight of thy griefe for their offences, may worke also a griefe in them that offend. But if notwithstanding all this, thou wilt make a pastime of sinne, and reioyce in iniquitie, I say no more, but that so doing,
<note place="margin">Ephes. 4.30.</note> thou doest grieue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirit, and delight the vnholy spirit, the diuell: for if those hellish spirits can haue any delight, this is their delight, to see men sinne, and to make a sport of it. And now if thou wilt be the Diuels Chanter, or Singing-man, if thou wilt grieue the holy spirit, to delight the hellish spirits, why then goe on, he that is vniust, let him be vniust still, and he that's filthy, let him be filthy still, and see what will come of it.
<note place="margin">Rev. 22. v. 11.</note> If God be true in his word, (as he is most true) they will proue <hi>bitter pleasures,</hi> Prov. 5.4. <hi>sorrowfull laughters, and mournefull mirthes,</hi> Prov. 14 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXXII That we should not faint in afflictions,but patiently endure in regard of the ioy that is set before vs, and the glory which shall be revealed in vs</head>
               <p>Thus our Saviour Christ.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12. v. 1. Heb. 11.25.29.</note>
                  <hi>For the ioy which was set before him he endured the Crosse, despising the shame.</hi> So Moses, <hi>for the hope of the recompence of reward,</hi> which was in mercy
<pb facs="tcp:177089:47"/>promised him, <hi>he refused to be called the sonne of</hi> Pharoahs <hi>Daughter, and chose rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, then to enioy the pleasures of sinne for a season,</hi> and this is written for our learning.</p>
               <p>And we may gather also some helpe to further our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning herein, out of the <hi>Booke of Nature.</hi> The diseased man endures cutting, searing, for a short vse of a miserable life; Shall we refuse to suffer any thing for the ioy that is set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs? For the glory that shall be revealed in vs? Specially considering,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 18.</note> that <hi>the sufferings of this present time are not worthy of the glory, to be revealed in vs,</hi> as the Apostle saith. Not worthy to be named on that day, that this glory is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. The sufferings being short and finite, and the glory infinite. Let not the loue of a short miserable life procure more patience of vs, then the loue of an eternall, ioyfull, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious life: rather let <hi>the same mind be in you, which was also in</hi> Moses, <hi>and in Christ Iesus, who for the ioy and glory that was set before them, endured the Crosse, and despised the shame,</hi> Heb. 12.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXXIII That we should not seeke to please it ching eares,that is, such as desire to heare novelties, and nicities, rather then the wholsome and sauing doctrine of faith and repentance.</head>
               <p>Thus it is written.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4 13. 2. Tim. 2 v. 15.16.</note>
                  <hi>Giue attendance to reading, to exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to doctrine. Studie to shew thy selfe approued vnto God, a workeman that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the word of truth. But shunne profane and vaine bablings, for they increase vnto more vngodlynesse. Foolish and vnlearned questions avoyd, knowing that they doe gender strifes,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.23. 1 Tim. 6.3.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> will giue vs some help to like well of this course. when we leaue good nourishing meat, and feed vpon some roote, or toy, it is a signe of queasie, and crude stomacks: so
<pb facs="tcp:177089:47"/>when hearers regard not to heare the wholsome doctrine of faith &amp; repentance, but rather delight to be nibling on a root of discipline, or ceremonie, it is a signe of much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and crudity, which would be purged rather then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> thought himselfe a very eloquent man,
<note place="margin">Hom. 38. ad populum.</note> writeth thus. <hi>This</hi> (saith he) <hi>subverteth the Church of God, that you desire not to heare sermons of compunction, but rather such which may delight, by an Elegant composition of words and phrases: And that we (which is wonderfull ill) follow your humours, which we should pare away.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXXIIII That it is good for our soules health to be walking diligently in the duties of our profession.</head>
               <p>Thus the Holy <hi>Apostle</hi> Paul, having said to his heaers, the Ephesians, Awake thou that sleepest, and stand vp from the dead, and Christ shall giue thee life, and so hauing row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed &amp; raised vp their soules from the drowsinesse &amp; deadli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of sinne; he prescribes them a meanes to keepe and preserue their soules wakeing, and in good health, and that is circumspect walking.
<note place="margin">Ephes. 5. v. 15.</note>
                  <hi>See that yee walke circumspect by</hi> (saith he) <hi>not as fooles, but as wise, redeeming the time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this <hi>Nature</hi> shewes to be a good meanes to keepe and preserue the soule in good case and state. For as walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and stirring helpe to evocate, and breathe out peccant humors, to the preseruing of the health of the body: So spirtuall exercises, and to be walking dilgently and conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably in the duties of our profession, furthers and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues the health of thesoule.</p>
               <p>Through sloth, and idlenesse, sound bodies haue beene Corrupted. And so after saving grace receiued, if we be not stirring and practising; Corruption, the world, pride, vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse or sinne or other will grow vpon vs.
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.6.</note> Wherefore if you desire the welfare of your soules give diligenee to <hi>stirre vp the gift of God that is in you,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith. Vp and be
<pb facs="tcp:177089:48"/>doing. Be doing, and conscionably walking in the duties of our profession, and calling, both generall, of Christianities, and particular, wherein yee liue in the Church, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or family. Labour in this kind is profitable both to soule, and body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="doctrine">
               <head>LXXV That the authority of the Church is not aboue,nor yet equall with the authority of the Scripture.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the Holy Ghost by the mouth of the Apostle,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note>
                  <hi>If we receiue the testimonie, or</hi> witnesse <hi>of men, the testimonie of God is greater.</hi> And now the testimonie of the Church is the testimonie of men; and the testimonie of the scripture is the testimonie of God:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.1. Psal. 12.7.</note> And shall not this be greater, and of greater authoritie? Shall mens voice and testimonie be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Gods? See how the very <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> Cries downe this.</p>
               <p>By the order and Course which <hi>God</hi> hath set downe in <hi>Nature,</hi> we see that the <hi>voice</hi> and <hi>authoritie</hi> of the <hi>spouse</hi> is <hi>inferiour</hi> to the <hi>voice</hi> and <hi>authoritie</hi> of the <hi>Bride-groome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. v. 32.</note>
                  <hi>The husband hath authoritie ouer his wife, as long as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> being witnesse: And if he die, leauing his will and testament behind him, she cannot administer as she will,
<note place="margin">Esa. 54. v. 5.</note> but as his will requires: And now <hi>Christ</hi> is the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome,</hi> or husband of his <hi>Church.</hi> And the <hi>Church,</hi> is his <hi>spouse</hi> or wife: And Christ, the husband of this spouse, is not dead,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1. v. 18.</note> but aliue, and <hi>aliue for euermore.</hi> Indeed <hi>Christ</hi> died concerning sinne once, and is departed from the Church his spouse for a while in respect of his bodily presence; But he did not dye intestate or without a <hi>will;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3. v. 21.</note> before he departed, he made a <hi>will,</hi> and left it behind him at his going away: and this not an vncertaine <hi>Nuncupatiue</hi> will,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. v 39. Mat. 26. v. 28.</note> but a certaine written will: a <hi>will</hi> with <hi>two seales,</hi> which is the <hi>Scripture</hi> with the <hi>two Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What meaneth then the people of Rome in crying out, <hi>The Church, the Church,</hi> or <hi>the spouse the spouse,</hi> the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb facs="tcp:177089:48"/>of the Church, or spouse is greater? What is not <hi>Christ,</hi> the bride-groome aliue, That the spouse should carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the name, and sway and rule? I hold it good, that as wee should honour God, our Father: So wee should ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Church our Mother, with the honour due vnto her: But why should the Mother haue the chiefest honour, the highest authority: Why should they be all for the wife, and little or nothing for the Husband? Verily I see no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, nor honesty in this.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.12. 1. Cor. 7.</note>
                  <hi>I suffer not a woman to vsurpe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the man,</hi> saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> it is vnsufferable in his opinion, and <hi>he spake by the spirit of God.</hi> And the truth is, if their Church were an honest woman (that is Christs owne spouse) vnlesse they would make much of her husband Christ and his word, she would not be made much of them. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> But now Christ is departed from his Church in respect of his bodily presence, so that now his Church is left to her selfe, as it were a widdow. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
                  </label> True, Christ is now departed from his Church for a little space, in regard of his bodily presence, as the Scripture saith;
<note place="margin">Act. 1.9. &amp;. C. 3.21.</note> though the <hi>Romanists</hi> will haue him to be still corporally present in their Sacrament: But though he be departed for a certaine space, yet he hath not left the <hi>Church</hi> (his spouse) to administer vpon the whole stocke, according as shee please in the meane time: no, not so, he made a will and testament, (as I told you) (which is the Scripture) and hee hath commanded the Church, his spouse, to execute that, and not her owne will:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.6.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.18.19.</note> to execute it truly and faithfully, without adding to, or diminishing from it, or any way corrupting it, so that there is no ground for the Church, to preferre, or to equall her will and authority, with her husbands will, which is the Scripture.</p>
               <p>What then may the Church of Rome pretend for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or at least equalling her will and authority, with the will and authority of Christ in the Scripture? their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I find to be these, that the Church is the keeper and witnesse of the Scripture; the pillat and foundation of the
<pb facs="tcp:177089:49"/>Scripture; the discerner of true Scripture from false &amp; sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posititious writings; the interpreter &amp; publisher of the Scripture; in briefe, that we cannot know Scripture to be Scripture but by the Church.</p>
               <p>Now see the weaknesse of these pretences and grounds to build vpon. We doe not know the Scripture to be Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the Church say they. No? May not a man hauing eyes perceiue the light of the Sunne without the meanes of any other light? May not a man know day by day-light? Even so a man that is not blind in his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and hath his eyes opened and annointed by the <hi>eye-salue</hi> of Gods spirit, may perceiue the Suripture to bee Scripture by the very light of Scripture it selfe, by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine maiesty of God shining bright, and speaking to vs therein.</p>
               <p>But let all these things be granted, that the Church is the keeper, the witnesse, the discerner, the interpreter and publisher, the pillar and foundation of Scripture, yet all this doth not proue that her authority is aboue, or equall with the Scripture. No, not in <hi>naturall wisdome;</hi> for what if a woman keepes her husbands will, and proues it, and beares witnesse to it when time serues, is shee therefore of greater authority then her husband? And is her will before or equall with his? Hath a jewell his excellency from the keeper or from it selfe? Doth a witnesse make or manifest truth?
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4. v. 28.29. Ioh. 1.15. Act. 2.32. c. 10.43.</note> Why? the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> bare witnesse of Christ, was she therefore of more credence, and greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then Christ? Iohn Baptist, and the Apostles, and all the Prophets bare witnesse of Christ, were they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of Greater authority then Christ?</p>
               <p>I but the Church is not only a witnesse, but a discerner of true Scripture; True, the Church hauing the spirit of Christ, can discerne true Scripture from false and supposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious writings, but how? Not by her owne iudgement, but by the helpe of Scripture, as a Gold-smith, by a touch-stone doth not make gold but try and discerne Gold from
<pb facs="tcp:177089:49"/>other mettalls: So the <hi>Church</hi> hauing the spirit of Christ, can discerne Scripture by the touch-stone of <hi>Scripture:</hi> and hauing the gift of prophesie. Shee can interpret Scripture, but alwaies remembred by Scripture: shee is not a <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriall</hi> but a <hi>Ministeriall inrerpreter;</hi> shee cannot make Scripture, no more then a Gold-smith can make Gold, but only discerne, and manifest Scripture by Scripture.</p>
               <p>I, but the <hi>Church is the pillar and foundation of the truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. v. 15.</note> as the Apostle saith, and as the <hi>Romanists</hi> doe much vrge. What then? Is shee therefore the rule of truth? or the word of truth? Why, a <hi>King</hi> puts forth a <hi>Proclamation</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his will and pleasure, to be obserued by his subiects, and he commaunds his officers to publish it, and to fasten it to a pillar or post in some publike place, that all may see and know it. Now because the <hi>Kings officer</hi> proclaimes and publishes the Kings pleasure, is he therefore of greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then the King? Or because the Proclamation is fastned to a pillar or post, and the post vpholds it, is the <hi>Post</hi> therefore of geater authority then the Proclamation? No man will say so: Why so it is here; <hi>God</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> hath put forth his proclamation concerning his will, which is the holy Scripture, and he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Church to publish it, and vphold it by her Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, as a pillar, or post vpholdeth a Proclamation, or a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Lawes and statutes: Now because God hath made the Church as it were a pillar to shew and vphold his truth, must she therefore be the rule of truth? Or equall with the word of truth? Doth an <hi>Herald</hi> or <hi>Cryer</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes the Kings pleasure, giue any authority to it? Or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifest his pleasure? <hi>Let God be true then,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 3.4.</note>
                  <hi>and every man a lyar,</hi> who denies the supreme authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">Th words of the Lord are pure words; as siluer tried.</note> and let that punishment light vpon them that adde to or detract from Gods word, which belongs, and is wont to be executed vpon those that clippe the Kings siluer, or goe about to coine without his commission, even death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they repent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="doctrine">
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:50"/>
               <head>LXXVII That the plea of the Papists in saying that their religion is the old religion,and their Church the Catholique Church, is not sufficient to proue their Church and religion to be true.</head>
               <p>Thus saith the word of truth.
<note place="margin">Prou. 16. v. 31.</note>
                  <hi>The hoary head</hi> (or old age) <hi>is a crowne of glory,</hi> but how? <hi>If it be found in the way of righteousnesse.</hi> All kinde of eldership and antiquity is not honourable and acceptable before God, or men. If a man be an <hi>old adulterer that doteth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles 25.2.</note> such a one <hi>my soule hateth</hi> faith the wise man. If eldership and antiquity were suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to commend things vnto vs, then all should bee well, all things should be good, sinne, and error, yea and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himselfe should be good: for he is old and auncient, even as auncient as the world within a little, and so errour and vice is not much short of truth &amp; vertue for antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.21.27. v. 33. v. 43.</note>
                  <hi>yee haue heard by them of old time,</hi> saith <hi>Christ, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not commit adultery. Thou shalt not forsweare thy selfe. Thou shalt loue thy Neighbour, and hate thy Enemie, &amp;c.</hi> And so how men haue corrupted the law with their false glosses, expounding it altogether of the outward act: so that as truth and vertue is old and ancient, so likewise is error and vice. As there is an ancient truth: so there is an old error and <hi>corruption</hi> which the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls the <hi>old man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 22.</note> because it is as old as humane nature, euen very neere as old as <hi>Adam</hi> our first Parent. And as <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> superstition, &amp; vice is old &amp; ancient, so also is it <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique,</hi> that is generall and vniversall, as the word doth signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; it is as <hi>Catholique</hi> and vniversall as truth and vertue it selfe;
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.19. Mat. 7.</note> or rather more <hi>Catholique</hi> and generall; for <hi>the whole world lyeth in wickednesse,</hi> and but a few in verity and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Error and vice are as Catholique as truth and vertue, in all kinde of respects in this world, they are Catholique in respect of times, of places, of persons, of all ages, sexe and conditions. What times? what places? what persons?
<pb facs="tcp:177089:50"/>what ages, sexe and conditions of men haue beene altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free from errors and vice? the scriprute speakes of none such.</p>
               <p>What is the matter then, that the <hi>Romanists</hi> doe so glory in the oldnesse and catholiquenesse of their faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>receaued by tradition from their fathers?</hi> Why a mans faith and religion may be so old and catholique, as that it may be the worse for it, as if it be an old, and a catholique errour or superstition, as theirs is, in those things wherein they differ from vs. Tis true, the saying is to bee allowed &amp; receaued, <hi>Bonum quò antiquius eò melius, &amp; quò communius eo melius,</hi> A good thing the more ancient, &amp; the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and generall it is, the better it is: But (alwaies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred) it must be <hi>bonum good,</hi> if it cease to bee <hi>bonum, good,</hi> then <hi>quò antiquius, &amp; communius, eò peius,</hi> the more ancient &amp; the more catholique or common it is, the worse it is: &amp; so is the <hi>Romish faith,</hi> or faction, the more ancient &amp; catholike it is, the worse it is, because it is not <hi>vera &amp; bona fides,</hi> a true and a sound faith. If they can proue that their religion is old and true, and not erroneous, and their <hi>Church a holy catholique Church,</hi> and not an <hi>vnholy catholique strumpet,</hi> then it is well, then we will ioyne with them: but to doe this they must doe more then ever they haue done hitherto, since their fall: yea and in very truth, it is more then ever they will be able truely to doe in the points wherein they differ from vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be no more children then, tossed to and fro,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. v. 14.</note>
                  <hi>&amp; carried about with every winde of doctrine, by the sleight of men, &amp; cunning craftinesse, whereby they lye in waight to deceaue,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle saith. Let not every doctrine that carries a shew of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and catholiquenesse or vniversality presently win your loue and liking, for there is antiquity and an vniversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of errour, as well as of truth. <hi>Custome without truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian. Epist. 74.</note>
                  <hi>is but antiquitie of errour,</hi> as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> saith. Proue then antiquitie by truth, rather then truth by antiquity, that is the safer course.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:51"/>
               <p>I might goe on farther in this worke of <hi>Translation</hi> which I haue here begunne: but because my desire herein is more to profit others then my selfe, I here containe my selfe, till I see the event.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christian Reader,</hi> by this which I haue done, thou maist see how that many and profitable instructions may be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by reading the small <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> Thy selfe. And now if thou wilt accept of my counsell, I would advise thee to read and study thy selfe, thine owne body with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, station, office, and vse of the members thereof. And to learne things heauenly, by considering of things earthly, to learne spirituall by naturall things.</p>
               <p>The <hi>plea of ignorance</hi> is a <hi>common plea,</hi> and goes for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Alas Sir, we are ignorant and not booke-learned; or we want teachers, is the common and maine excuse of many men and women, when they are told of their faults.</p>
               <p>Well, say it be so, that thou art not <hi>Booke-learned,</hi> as that thou canst not read thy Bible, or the Booke of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet thou maist read the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> thy selfe: that is alwaies at hand, and freely bestowed vpon thee without any charge:
<note place="margin">Abac 2.2.</note> that is plaine and easie, as that thou maist runne and read, or at least spell what thy dutie is, that is portable and easie of carriage, for thou canst goe no where but thou must carry that Booke about thee. Look then into it some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, if thou canst not, or if thou hast no list or leasure to read the Scripture, as some wickedly vse to say: why then looke into the <hi>Booke of Nature,</hi> Thy selfe, and thereby learne heauenly wisdome there is <hi>enough to make thee without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 1. v. 20.</note> There is a <hi>double vse</hi> to bee made of every creature, the one <hi>Naturall,</hi> the other <hi>Spirituall:</hi> Content not thy selfe with the naturall vse, without the spirituall: Doe as <hi>Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> in a far country, make of every thing thou seest a good instruction, and every action a stirrop to heauenly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I haue shewed thee in some measure how to read Thy selfe, how to translate this <hi>Booke of Nature</hi> into the <hi>vse of Grace</hi> now this doe. This study may become the best and
<pb facs="tcp:177089:51"/>learned'st of vs all, it was <hi>King Davids study,</hi> Psalme 139.14.17.</p>
               <p>But I haue read this Lecture principally for their sake, who vse to plead ignorance, and to say they are not booke-learned, or that they want teachers, and so thinke to excuse themselues in their sinnes; Here I haue shewed that this pretence &amp; excuse will not serue, because the very <hi>Booke of nature</hi> is sufficient to cut off this excuse: or to vse the words of the Apostle, because <hi>the invisible things of God, from the creation of the world</hi> (and in particular from the creation of man) <hi>are clearely seene being vnderstood by the things that are made,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note>
                  <hi>even his eternall power and God-head so that they are without excuse.</hi> Consider then the things that are made, <hi>consider Thyselfe,</hi> and thereby get vnderstanding. <hi>Consider what I haue said vnto thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. v. 2.7.</note>
                  <hi>and the Lord giue thee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in all things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:52"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 25. read beatissimae for baptissimae, p. 9. l. 2. r. diseased f. displeased, p. 19. l. 6. dele they, p. 20. l. 20. deleowne, p. 53. r. sparkles f sparkes, p. 87. l. 24. r. evacuate f. evocate, ib. l. 26. r. spitituall f. spir tuall. P. 4. 1 in marg. r. Par. in Rom. f. Par. in. &amp; Rom. 5.10. f. Rom. 6.9. p. 22. r. Eccles. f. C.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:52"/>
            <head>The heads of certaine doctrines delivered in the Booke of Grace, and here illustrated by the Booke of Nature, are these,</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>That there is a God.</hi> Page. 2.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>That there is a Trinity of Persons, in the vnity of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Essence, and an vnity of Essence in the Trinity of Persons.</hi> Page. 4.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>That our Lord Iesus Christ the Sonne of God, is God and Man.</hi> Page. 5.</item>
               <item>4 <hi>That Iesus Christ the Sonne of God is Coeternall with the Father.</hi> Page. 5.</item>
               <item>5 <hi>That God in his Nature and Attributes is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensible.</hi> Page. 6.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>That the knowledge of God, and of the things of God, is to be learned of God himselfe in his word.</hi> Page. 7.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>That there is but one means of salvation even Christ.</hi> Page. 7</item>
               <item>8 <hi>That we must haue a sense and a sorrow for our sinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can be saved by Christ.</hi> Page. 8.</item>
               <item>9 <hi>That wee must consider our waies and take notice of our sinnes, and misery, before we can truly repent, and turne to God.</hi> Page. 10.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>That confession of sinnes brings peace to the soule, and quietnesse to the heart.</hi> Page. 10.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:53"/>
               <item>11 <hi>That we should not be deiected in mind, or cast away our hope by reason of troubles of minde, streights of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or vexation of Spirit.</hi> Page. 11.</item>
               <item>12 <hi>That the soule is immortall.</hi> Page. 12.</item>
               <item>13 <hi>That there shall be a resurrection of the body.</hi> Page. 13.</item>
               <item>14 <hi>That the salvation of those which truly repent, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly beleeue the holy Gospell, is sure and certaine.</hi> Page. 14.</item>
               <item>15 <hi>That no man hearing of Gods eternall predestination, and vnchangeable decree, is to cast away the care of a good life.</hi> Page. 15.</item>
               <item>16 <hi>That God is not the author of sinne.</hi> Page. 16.</item>
               <item>17 <hi>That we should not be questioning of hidden things, or of those things which are not profitable to know.</hi> Page. 17.</item>
               <item>18 <hi>That wee are to ascribe the praise and glory of all the good wee thinke, speake, or doe, to the goodnesse and praise of God, and not to our owne good nature.</hi> Page. 18</item>
               <item>19 <hi>That we are to raise our affections from earthly things, and to set them on things that are aboue.</hi> Page. 19.</item>
               <item>20 <hi>That the things of this world are not satisfactory, or able to fill and content the mind of man.</hi> Page. 21.</item>
               <item>21 <hi>That we ought to endeavour to grow every day better and better and to increase in grace.</hi> Page. 23.</item>
               <item>22 <hi>That wee doe not liue the life of grace, vnlesse wee bee actiue and stirring in well doing; desirous and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in seeking the preservation thereof, sensible of what may hurt it, and carefull to resist it.</hi> Page. 24.</item>
               <item>23 <hi>That wee cannot liue the life of grace, except wee attend vpon the word of grace, the holy scripture.</hi> Page. 26.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>That wee must take heed of omitting that good which wee should doe, as well as of committing that evill which wee should not doe, if wee desire to saue, and not to loose our soules.</hi> Page. 26.</item>
               <item>25 <hi>That no man is to neglect the preaching of the Gospell, because God can saue without it.</hi> Page. 29</item>
               <item>26 <hi>That no man be he ever so eminent for learning, for wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:177089:53"/>for wealth and honour, is to neglect the hearing of Gods word, and exercising himselfe therein.</hi> Page. 30.</item>
               <item>27 <hi>That superiours, and men of great and eminent place, or grace aboue others, are not to despise and contemne their inferiours, for their low and meane estate beneath them.</hi> Page. 32.</item>
               <item>28 <hi>That inferiours ought not to envy their superiours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of their greatnesse aboue them, but to bee content with their place.</hi> Page. 33.</item>
               <item>29 <hi>That we ought to haue a sympathy, or fellow-feeling of one anothers misery, and to be ready to helpe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another.</hi> Page. 34.</item>
               <item>30 <hi>That wee should endeavour with all diligence to hold v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and concord one with another.</hi> Page. 35.</item>
               <item>31 <hi>That to revenge our selues, especially in every petty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, is a signe of great weaknesse, and not of a good spirit or mettall.</hi> Page. 37.</item>
               <item>32 <hi>That wee should avoid all busy medling with things not belonging to vs, and beyond the bounds of our call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Page. 37</item>
               <item>33 <hi>That we should seeke the common good, and not our owne private alone.</hi> Page. 38.</item>
               <item>34 <hi>That wee should honour, and obey the higher powers, the Magistrates and Ministers.</hi> Page. 39.</item>
               <item>35 <hi>That wee should be willing to be at charge, and to take paines for the maintenance of the King and state.</hi> Page. 40.</item>
               <item>36 <hi>That the life and wellfare of our supreame head and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, the King, is to be tendred, and preferred before our owne, or any other mans life or wellfare.</hi> Page. 42.</item>
               <item>37 <hi>That they should behaue themselues well, both in word and deed, that be superiours.</hi> Page. 42.</item>
               <item>38 <hi>That Governours and Commanders should regard soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, and giue them maintenance.</hi> Page. 43.</item>
               <item>39 <hi>That iustice iustly executed is the life and wellfare of the common-wealth.</hi> Page. 44.</item>
               <item>40 <hi>That there is but one Church.</hi> Page. 45.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:54"/>
               <item>41 <hi>That Christ is the supreame head of the Church and not the Pope.</hi> Page. 45</item>
               <item>42 <hi>That the Romane Church is not the Catholique Church.</hi> Page. 54.</item>
               <item>43 <hi>That wee ought to approue of the imparity of callings, and the vnquall division of Gods gifts in the Church.</hi> Page. 48.</item>
               <item>44. <hi>That the Church of Rome is not to be the better thought of, for her outward pompe and glory: nor the Church of England, and the rest of the reformed Churches the worst to be thought of, for their plaine and meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state.</hi> Page. 49.</item>
               <item>45 <hi>That the Church of England is not to be forsaken, or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from, by reason of some supposed errours, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions therein.</hi> Page. 50.</item>
               <item>46 <hi>That the voice of God sounding in his written word the Holy Scripture, is the speaking decider of all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies in the Church.</hi> Page. 53.</item>
               <item>47 <hi>That wee ought to deny our selues (that is our owne iudgements, our owne wills and affections, our owne works and worthinesse) And to follow Christ, by beleeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him as our only Saviour, and obeying him as our chiefe Lord.</hi> Page. 55.</item>
               <item>48 <hi>That Parents, and all Masters of families, should bee carefull to purge and ridde their houses of all Idolaters, and other willfull and obstinate sinners.</hi> Page. 56.</item>
               <item>49 <hi>That all both men and women, high &amp; low, should frame themselues to goe after their place and estate, and to vse that habit or fashion that is meet for them.</hi> Page. 57</item>
               <item>50 <hi>That we should not be forward to censure or iudge to other men.</hi> Page. 59.</item>
               <item>51 <hi>That God is omniscient, and knoweth all things that wee doe speake, or thinke.</hi> Page. 59.</item>
               <item>52 <hi>That the wisdome and power of God in the making and framing of the body of man, is wonderfull and praise-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi> Page. 60.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:177089:54"/>
               <item>53 <hi>That God only is most louely, and loue worthy.</hi> Page. 62.</item>
               <item>54 <hi>That wee ought to heare only such things as come from God.</hi> Page. 65.</item>
               <item>55 <hi>That we should be swift to heare and slow to speake.</hi> Page. 65.</item>
               <item>56 <hi>That wee should ioyne practise and profession together</hi> Page. 66.</item>
               <item>57 <hi>That wee can never haue a good heart, as long as wee haue a bad tongue, and lead an evill life.</hi> Page. 66.</item>
               <item>58 <hi>That we should not abuse our tongues to the dishonouring of God by swearing, or to the defaming of men by slander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any kind of evill speaking.</hi> Page. 67.</item>
               <item>59 <hi>That we should not open our eyes to every obiect.</hi> Page. 68.</item>
               <item>60 <hi>That wee should be very carefull to keepe and preserue our spirituall sight, the eye of faith, from any hurt or blemish.</hi> Page. 69</item>
               <item>61 <hi>That wee should abhorre idlenesse and every one walke in a lawfull calling, endeavouring to doe the best good we can, with the gifts which God hath given vs.</hi> Page. 71.</item>
               <item>62 <hi>That the greater our zeale, paines and travell hath bin, is, or shall be in Gods cause, the greater shall bee the weight of our glory.</hi> Page. 37.</item>
               <item>63 <hi>That we should not be disheartned from doing the duties of our calling, because we cannot worke that good which wee desire.</hi> Page. 73</item>
               <item>64 <hi>That we should not goe beyond our gifts.</hi> Page. 75.</item>
               <item>65 <hi>That Parents should accommodate their children to a fit calling.</hi> Page. 77.</item>
               <item>66 <hi>That ignorance is the cause of sinne, and also of most fearfull destruction.</hi> Page. 78.</item>
               <item>67 <hi>That we should be very carefull that we doe not witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and willingly offend against the checks of conscience, and the cleere light of Gods word.</hi> Page. 79.</item>
               <item>68 <hi>That we should not venture vpon the committing of any the least sinne, vpon presumption of Gods mercy, or in hope of future repentance.</hi> Page. 86.</item>
               <item>69 <hi>That wee must take speciall heed of recidivation, or fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:177089:55"/>into the same sinne againe, after wee haue once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented thereof, and forsaken it.</hi> Page. 81</item>
               <item>70 <hi>That wee should not iudge of them as reprobates or cast-awaies, who hauing professed Christ &amp; his religion, afterwards fall there-from in time of persecution, or some strong temptation.</hi> Page. 82</item>
               <item>71 <hi>That wee should not make the sinnes and infirmities, or the miseries of other men, a matter of our mirth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, but of our sorrow and heavinesse.</hi> Page. 84</item>
               <item>72 <hi>That we should not faint in afflictions, but patiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, in regard of the ioy that is set before vs, and the glory that shall be revealed in vs.</hi> Page. 85,</item>
               <item>73 <hi>That we should not seeke to please itching eares, that is, such as desire to heare novelties, rather then the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine of faith and repentance.</hi> Page. 86.</item>
               <item>74 <hi>That it is good for our soules health to be walking dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in the duties of our profession.</hi> Page. 87.</item>
               <item>75 <hi>That the authority of the Church is not aboue, nor yet equall with the authority of the scripture.</hi> Page. 88.</item>
               <item>76 <hi>That the plea of the Papists, in saying, their Religion is the old Religion, and their Church is the Catholique Church, is not sufficient to proue their Church and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to be true.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177089:55"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>